<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tutela sanitatis sive Vita protracta The protection of long life, and detection of its brevity, from diætic causes and common cutoms. Hygiastic præcautions and rules appropriate to the constitutions of bodyes; and various discrasyes or passions of minde; dayly to be observed for the preservation of health and prolougation of life. With a treatise of fontinells or issues. Whereunto is annexed Bellum necessarium sive Medicus belligerans the military or practical physitian reveiwing [sic] his armory: furnished with medical weapons munition against the secret invaders of life; fitted for all persons and assaults; with their safe and regular use, according to medical art and discipline by Everard Maynwaring doctor in physick.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213837</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826106</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30498</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1798:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tutela sanitatis sive Vita protracta The protection of long life, and detection of its brevity, from diætic causes and common cutoms. Hygiastic præcautions and rules appropriate to the constitutions of bodyes; and various discrasyes or passions of minde; dayly to be observed for the preservation of health and prolougation of life. With a treatise of fontinells or issues. Whereunto is annexed Bellum necessarium sive Medicus belligerans the military or practical physitian reveiwing [sic] his armory: furnished with medical weapons munition against the secret invaders of life; fitted for all persons and assaults; with their safe and regular use, according to medical art and discipline by Everard Maynwaring doctor in physick.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Peter Lillicrap. And sold by S. Thompson stationer at the Bishops head in St. Pauls Church-yard: T. Basset stationer under St. Dunstans Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect; as filmed Bodleian Library copy only includes title page and final leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tutela Sanitatis.</hi> SIVE <hi>VITA PROTRACTA.</hi> THE Protection of long Life, and Detection of its brevity, from diaetetic Cauſes and common Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>Hygiaſtic Praecautions and Rules appropriate to the Conſtitutions of bodyes; and various Diſcraſyes or Paſſions of Minde; dayly to be obſerved for the preſervation of Health and Prolongation of Life. WITH A Treatiſe of Fontinells or Iſſues.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is Annexed <hi>BELL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M NECESSARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M</hi> SIVE <hi>MEDIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S BELLIGERANS</hi> THE Military or Practical Phyſitian Reveiwing his Armory: Furniſhed with Medicinal Weapons and Munition againſt the ſecret invaders of life; fitted for all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and aſſaults; with their ſafe and regular uſe, according to medical art and diſcipline</p>
            <p>By <hi>Everard Maynwaring</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Toga conuenit armis</l> ET <l>Bellum gero, pro bono pub lico.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Peter Lillicrap. And ſold by S. Thompſon Stationer at the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops head in St. Pauls Church-yard: T. Baſſer Stationer under St. Dunſtans Church in Fleet-Sreet. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To His Renowned Highneſs RUPERT, COUNT PALATINE</hi> of the <hi>Rhene, Duke of</hi> Cumberland, <hi>Kt. of the Garter, &amp;c. Health, Happineſs and long Life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath beene the Cuſtome of paſt Ages to prefix ſome Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Perſonage in the Front of their Works, partly to ſhew a reſpect to Dignity and Honour, and to reverence the Excellency and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Eminency of the Perſon; as alſo their peculiar exemplary Merits
<pb facs="tcp:30498:3"/>and Endowments ſuting with, and favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Treatiſe: I am hence imboldened in this Dedication to ſet Your Highneſs a Patron, as you may be a Pattern of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and regular living. Health and long Life, two great deſiderable Injoyments, the one a ſtep to the other, and both acquired (by the courſe of Nature) in the methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and regular obſervance of <hi>Diaetetic</hi> Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Endowments and Faculties of the Mind, are much diſpoſed and Biaſſed, heighthened and abated in their operations, by the Temperament and Conſtitutional Changes of the Body; and that alſo by a ſeminal power and vertue from Parents, the ill effects and products of irregular and a methodical living is implanted and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractarized in their off-ſpring; Therefore the regular tuition and government of the Body is of great concernment to all; but more eſpecially to ſuch, who more eminently
<pb facs="tcp:30498:3"/>are ſerviceable in a Kingdom, and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted as Pillars of Honour to ſupport and bear up the ſpreading Fame and Renown of our Nation for Heroick Worthies: That we may not untimely be deprived of ſuch, nor of our hopes in their Noble and Illuſtrious ſucceeding Progeny. And as a Duty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with my nature, the propagation of Honourable renowned Families, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from a degenerate Iſſue, by prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautions and wholſom Rules, is much inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by theſe Endeavors.</p>
            <p>I now crave your Highneſs acceptance of this ſmall Offering, the Fruit of my Study and Labor; which may ſerve as a Directory in the dayly uſe of thoſe requiſites neceſſary to being and well being: In the regular courſe of which by a Decree in Nature, is promiſed Sanity, length of dayes, and juvenile vigour; that as your Highneſs is eminently placed in Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Power, your natural Endowments
<pb facs="tcp:30498:4"/>alſo and perſonal Abilities, may not be clouded with the untimely defects of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor impedited in the full fruition and free injoyment of Temporal Happineſs; which ſhall be the conſtant wiſhes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as hereby it is the endeavors of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſs moſt humble Servant <hi>Everard Maynwaringe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:4"/>
            <head>Literato Philiatro Lectori Salutem.</head>
            <p>PYrrhus Rex, deorum in templo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molaturus, hoc unum <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam exoptatiſſimum à diis immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus petebat. Inter omnia namque hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano generi chara ac utilia corporis ſanitas poſt animae ſalutem, in praetio ab omnibus, prae omnibus bonis, maxime habenda eſt. Quippe quod ea vacillante ac labante, nec animae functiones, nec corporis membra, ad munia ſua rite diſponuntur, ſed vel fractis viribus fatigata ſuccumbunt, vel more indebito pravè &amp; remiſſè operantur. Frons hilaris &amp; Serenus in Severiorem mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumque tranſit &amp; indies defloreſcit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſa juventus: Honores porrò &amp; divitiae, ſplendida illa fortunae bona (amiſſa ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate) ingrata ac ſepoſita parvi penduntur: Voluptates &amp; deliciae qualeſecun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſolitae, injucundae &amp; exoletae tranſeunt. Quae cum ita ſint, omni ſtudio &amp; labore ſedulò
<pb facs="tcp:30498:5"/>incumbendum, utquantum naturae viribus detur, vel artis ingenio excogitari poſſit, hanc vitam in multos annos ſartam tectam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tueamur. Et licet ex rei natura vitae perennitatem non expectamus eò quod poteſtates &amp; cauſae vitales à principiis facile inuicem diſſidentibus, Et ſeſe mutuò de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruentibus dependent; morborum ſaltem occaſiones &amp; incurſiones ſaepius praecaueri, juventutis effloreſcentiam, vigorem nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum &amp; viva citatem diutius conſervari, &amp; majori circulo vitae curſum peragi, nullis naturae legibus repugnat.</p>
            <p>Porrò cum vitae noſtrae ſcintilla va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis obiciatur injuriis, adeò ut fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cili negotio praefocari &amp; extingui poſſit; &amp; cum nihil in toto terrarum orbe hac vita ſalubri ſuavius obtineamus; nullis nec impenſis, nec curis, nec praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis parcendum, quantum in nobis, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae poteſtati conceſſum, à diminutione &amp; extinctione quam diutiſſimè conſervare &amp; protahere valeamus. In hunc finem ſanitatis hanc tutelam &amp; vitae praeſidium juxta nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae normam &amp; leges artis concinnatum, nulli non obtemperanti profuturum puto:
<pb facs="tcp:30498:5"/>opus non minus utile ſanis, quam aegris neceſſarium; viuere nam ſanos docet, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grotos valere. Prima pars benè vivendi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulas tradit, quo ſanitas praeſens diu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervetur; altera autem tutò medendi, quo amiſſa citò, paucis, parvo recuperetur. Habes (lector benevole) inſtituti mei ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, &amp; operis diviſionem: multa me reliquiſſe fateor ſtudiis futuris, &amp; me mihi ſatis nondum feciſſe; in poſterum verò, &amp; politiora haec &amp; plura edita fore curabo. Interea hiſcefave &amp; fruere, ut ſanitatem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando amiſſam quam primum reſtituas, preſentem feliciter tuearis. Jnde proemium hoc maximum multis ut proſim, valdè quaero. vale. dat. <hi>Londini</hi> 6 calend. <hi>Octobr.</hi> An. Dom. 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:6"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <p>Sept. 25. 1663.</p>
            <p>M. Franck <hi>S. T. P. Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto P. ac D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> Archi-Ep. Cant. à Sac. Dom.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:6"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>THe ſcope and intention of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal Art, at which every good Phyſitian collimes and aimes at, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to theſe two marks; Preſervation of the ſound, and Reſtoration of the Sick: and <hi>Janus</hi>-like he caſts a double Aſpect; to the healthy for their continuance; to the ſick for their recovery: nor is he leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd and rejoycing in natures proſperity and triumph, then ſubſidiary in her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; but ſhews the higheſt friendſhip in her declenſions and loweſt ebb. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving propoſed ſuch a Pattern for my imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have drawn the enſuing Work ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this examplar; which is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you now as a rough draught from the firſt hand, and ſhews you only the linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and proportion of the intended piece; but coming over it again by a reveiw, with the ſecond hand, as I purpoſe at my better leiſure and vacation from diſturbance; I
<pb facs="tcp:30498:7"/>hope ſomething of perfection may then be ſuperadded, and the life appear, which theſe dark lines do now but ſhaddow forth; and what I have touched but lightly, and unbratically exhibited to your view, ſhall more clearly and fully be delineated in the next impreſſion, in the interim take this as the earneſt of what I intend.</p>
            <p>The preſent work is divided in two parts; The firſt adviſeth and cautions the Sound; the latter directs and aſſiſts the Sick: That I may not ſeem leſs a friend to health, then an aſſiſtant in ſickneſs. The former part is diaetetical, and preſcribes lawes to govern the healthy; and rules out the pleaſant paths of health for them to walk in, that in the darkneſs of unadviſed precipitate ignorance, they ruſh not upon the ruine of a well tempored body, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe the harmony, and integrity of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, vital and animal faculties, which by natures courſe might continue much longer in their vigour then the common age, if not by folly and wilful erroneous practice, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently diſordered, debilitated and brought to untimely periods.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:7"/>
            <p>And that you may knowingly the better ſuite all your actions moſt proper and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordant with your own body and peculiar nature; your temperament and conſtitution by certaine characters and ſigns is diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thereby you may ſo order and govern your ſelf rationally and fitly, as each tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament particularly requires, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and plainely is preſcribed. And by diligent obſervation you will finde, in the courſe of life, your body to change and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much; ſometime to be Phlegmatick, ſometime Cholerick, another part of your life Melancholy to he predominant; as your condition of life, Diaetetic cuſtomes, &amp; progreſs in age, will diſpoſe and alter your conſtitution; which the peculiar figns of each preuailing humor will demonſtrate and evidently ſhew. Thoſe duely marked and the Hygiaſtic Rules juſtly obſerved, the age of man would be extended to a third part longer, many diſeaſes avoided, and ſcarce known which are now moſt obvious and frequent.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the folly and wilful error of the moſt, being prodigal of their lives and
<pb facs="tcp:30498:8"/>incautelous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nothing regarding what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to health and long life, but promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly follow and elect this or that, after the dictates of an irrational and ſenſitive deſire, To gratifie the preſent appetite in trivial and vaine ſatisfactions; thereby purchaſing ſhortneſs of dayes, accumulat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adding one diſtemper to another, debilitating one part after another by ſuch irregular and intemperate practice, until the body become a Hoſpital of diſeaſes, ſo complicated and contraindicating one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that a Colledge of Phyſitians is but ſufficient to conſult the reſtoration, if any for ſuch a perſon; when perhaps as yet he hath ſcarce numbred half his daies of the uſual age of man. But yet, the crime were leſs if onely to themſelves the prejudice did extend, but alſo to poſterity their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes are propagated; the children ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving impreſſed upon them, and radicated in the principles of their nature, the ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal power and productive vertue of inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, irregular, and intemperate living of their genitors and progenitors: that the children may bear witneſs to the following
<pb facs="tcp:30498:8"/>age, the vice and folly of their parents and praedeceſſors, recorded and characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized in them.</p>
            <p>But whoſoever deſires to live long, to ſee their Childrens children, to preſerve their youth, ſtrength &amp; beauty, to be free from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting pains &amp; loathſome diſeaſes, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their ſenſes &amp; enjoy the perfections of minde to the extremity of age; let them conforme and be obedient to the Higiaſtic lawes and rules herereafter preſcribed; and they may expect what is here propoſed for their reward. Nor ſhall I exact and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of you an irkeſome ſtrictneſs or Leſſian preciſeneſs to eate and drink by weight and meaſure: but a reaſonable obſervance, ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and well agreeing with a ſober ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perſon, not reſtraining convenient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and the lawful pleaſure of life. Nor can a regular courſe of life be thought trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome as a difficult and hard reſtraint, but moſt pleaſant and free, except to thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to the contrary; and the leaving of thoſe ill cuſtomes is the difficulty, but the rules injoyned be facile and eaſie to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:9"/>
            <q>
               <l>Non quia difficilia ſunt, multa non ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus;</l>
               <l>Sed quia non tentamus, difficilia ſunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And having once acquired a good habit and conſtant uſe, to returne to an irregular intemperate living, would be a far greater burthen and irkeſome, if enjoyned and impoſed, then the declining and deſerting a deſtructive courſe, for a laudable whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome practice, moſt conſonat to a rational creature, <hi>experto Crede—</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui medicè vivit, ſine medicis diu vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet:</l>
               <l>Qui non medicè vivit, cum medicis ſaepe, ſed non diu.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſecond or latter part of this Book is therapeutical, containing ſafe and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicaments for the ſick and infirme; breifly ſhewing their vertues, aproppriation uſe and doſes, but reſerving to my ſelf their compoſition and ingredients, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:30498:9"/>expected and deſired by ſome yet for ſufficient reaſons I thought beſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal. Firſt becauſe they are the arcana's of the medicinal Art, and ought not to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged to any but the ſons of art, who make it their buſineſs and ſtudy after ſuch inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Secondly, I write not to Phyſicians, but to thoſe who ſtand in need of ſuch, their adviſe and aſſiſtance; elſe my pen had run in another dialect, and the ſubject, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome novelty's to preſent. Thirdly, I will not undertake to teach you to be Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, or the Apothecaris art, and you muſt be knowing in both, or theſe medicines will availe you little. Fourthly, leaſt the medicines ſhould be abuſed, by ignorant pretenders to skill, endeavouring to make them, of which they are not capeable, and ſo defame good medicines, prejudice the author, and thoſe that ſhall uſe them. And farther, medicines does not belong to you, of other employments, profeſſions, trades, or who ever not authorized in the faculty; this belongs to the Phyſitian to know and appoint, as his propriety, and you to have the benefit and uſe of them, nor ought any
<pb facs="tcp:30498:10"/>to challenge the making of medicines as his right, but as ſubordinate, a ſervant of Phyſitians, to do the toyling part and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile work that belongs to it. And here I much admire how the trade of medicines firſt came up,: that a Phyſitian ſhould be ſo very ſtrict and exact in knowing the ſtate of his patient, not truſting to the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible inſufficient relation of another, but muſt view and examine the patient himſelf: Yet the remedy which is the main, that conflicts with the diſeaſe, wherein if there be a fault, the Doctors learning is of no effect; this is committed to the care, skill, honeſty of others, their ſervants and boyes, what reaſon is there for this? but when Phyſitians were few and ſcarce, practice very great and abundant, having not time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to viſit all their patients &amp; take their fees; Neglected medicines, threw off that care as a burthen, and relyed upon others, from whence hath ſprung not a few incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, and prejudice, to Phyſitians as well as the ſick; Which I forbear to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſince medicines is become a trade, it is a trade of the greateſt and
<pb facs="tcp:30498:10"/>moſt general concernment I know. And I muſt ſay, an error, miſtake or abuſe in the medicine is far greater and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, then a deficiency or error of the Phyſitian in his judgement of the Patient. For a good medicine is not ſo tyed up and reſtrained to one diſeaſe, But it ſhall ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate for good in many others, (ſeaſonably given in due quantity) ſo that if a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an do not ſo exactly determine a right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Patient; yet if the diſtemper he imagines, have but an affinity and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that which really afflicts the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and he gives a proper medicine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own determination, his medicine ſhall prevaile and ſucceed well. But an adulterate bad medicine, though given by the moſt skilful hand and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſultation, ſhall have bad effects: and therefore I may affirme, that a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of ordinary parts, with extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry curious medicines, ſhall performe more and greater cures, and have leſs miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, then the moſt knowing and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with ordinary, ſophiſticate medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. And I think it much more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:30498:11"/>that the Phyſitian ſhould look into the medicine then the chamber-pot, as a thing of greater concernment, and he ſhall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe with more ſecurity to his own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and leſs hazard to his patients life. And that Phiſitian who ſpends ſome time in Pharmacy- ſhall finde more ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſeeing a medicine duely prepared and compounded once, then in reading it a twelvemonth. From hence the true propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and quantity of each ingredient will exactly be known ſuting with the forme of the medicine, which incongrouſly I have ſeen preſcribed for want of knowledge in the pharmacopoietical part.</p>
            <p>From hence the particular proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and differing qulities of each ingredient will more plainely and fully be diſcovered in their ſingle preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, corrections, defecations, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and gradual mixtures, their conflict, diſcrepancy and rejection one of anothor in ſingle applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their mutual agreement em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces and union, in the whole compoſition by fit mediumes and artificial conjunction
<pb facs="tcp:30498:11"/>the diverſity of Taſtes and Smells reduced into one by fermentation the true colour, taſte, ſmell, conſiſtence and due form of the Medicine, will be diſcerned from a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inartificial ſophiſticate Medicine, and he that is not skilful practically in the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial making of Medicines, ſhall never rightly diſcern a good Medicine from a bad. Not that I think fit a Phyſician ſhould toyle in the drudgery of it; but a ſuperviſor of his Servants, to prevent miſtakes, abuſes, and ſlovenly operation. In vain the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian curiouſly inquires and ſtrictly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amines the ſtate of his Patient, if he be not as well aſcertained and fully ſatisfied in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Ingredient of the Medicine. He that practiſeth with unknown Medicines may be glad of his ſucceſs; but if the contrary hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen he ſhall not be ſatisfied where the fault was; whether in himſelf or the Medicine, the contumacy of the diſeaſe, or intervening accidents, nor can he note that an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for the future.</p>
            <q>Infaeliciter aegrotat ubi plus eſt periculi à medicamento quam à morbo.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:12"/>
            <p>Of the Druggs imported into <hi>England,</hi> a fourth part is more fit for the Dunghil then to come into the body of man; and he that takes a Medicine of that needs no other diſeaſe. Another fourth, though not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified corrupt and naught; yet weak, of ſmall vertue and efficacy, and a degenerate ſort; as much differing from the beſt, as they are in price, and that is double; and what think you becomes of theſe? they are not thrown away, when they are made up in medicine they paſs current.</p>
            <p>Beer that is made of Water, Hops and Mault three common things, and eaſie to be done after a common rule; and yet what variety of drinks, ſome good, ſome bad, differing in ſtrength, taſte, colour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence: So many Brewers, almoſt ſo many kinds of drink. What think you then of making Medicines, having twenty, thirty, forty, and ſome fifty Ingredients in the compoſition; and of theſe, many requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Single and ſeveral preparation and praevious ordering before they are fit for Compoſition; as correction, defaecation, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, trituration, diſſolution; coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:30498:12"/>calcination, torrefaction, inſolation, impregnation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Many more tedious to relate. Do you think now there is not more variety in the goodneſs and excellency of a Medicine of the ſame ſpecies and kinde, from ſeveral mens ordering and their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (differing in Art, care and honeſty) then in Beer or Ale made of two or three or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Ingredients, and eaſily diſcerned by the palate, ſmell or ſight. But the other of many, various, exotick ſtrange Druggs not known or heard of by the moſt in their age; producing a mixture, ſometimes not to be detected nor determined of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (although an Artiſt) but by operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the effects.</p>
            <q>Sine certa notitia medicamenti virtutum, non tuto curabit medicus</q>
            <p>From hence may be collected the reaſons and motives which firſt put me upon this work, and made me a Pharmacopoeian to my own practiſe. And being furniſhed with a large ſtock of Medicines peculiarly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and appointed for the moſt and principall occaſions that might occur in
<pb facs="tcp:30498:13"/>practiſe, and which I had often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with ſucceſs; and by due obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion found to be efficacious for their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate uſes; I was moved to communicate, and convert my private ſtock to a publick ſtore, for the benefit of thoſe who have not a fee ready, ſutable for a Doctor but muſt apply themſelves to bold profeſſing Empiricks, and other pragmatical fellows that deſerve to have their ears eut for their impudent ignorance in the practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and ſaucie uſurpation of ſo high and myſterious employment that the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men of the faculty in all ages have, and are ſtill in the diſquiſition; the many abuſes whereof in Medicines, and their improper uſe, is now the greateſt and moſt dangerous Cheat in this age: And if an account of the dead could be rightly taken, a third part would be found to have died, by nox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious or deficient Medicines, an illiterate pretender to Phyſick, or the imprudent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a friend or relation to the Sick. And it is not a ſtrange thing to Phyſitians who have obſerved, that Women ſometimes kill their own husbands and children giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:30498:13"/>them deadly draughts for ſanative poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The many ſad conſequents of this nature are ſo many, that it would take up more time and paper to relate then I can now ſpare, and therefore muſt wave the diſcourſe. <hi>Quiſque ſibi caveat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Magazine of Medicines, which here I own as my munition for practice, I have formed and reformed by exemplars from the neateſt inventions of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert renowned Doctors, Pharmacopoeians, Galenical and Chymical, both antient and modern. Pharmacy being the cheifeſt part of my Study and moſt delightful of late years. And having approved in practice what in reaſon they promiſed at the veiw, enticing to experiments, I may with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence commend to your uſe, being a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all that belongs to them; made choice of their Druggs, ſaw their due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and Compoſition; and not only a ſpectator, but an agent ſometimes, where the ſtricteſt care and niceſt curioſity is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, being the beſt recreation I know or can deſire: For my part, I deſire no other weapons to oppoſe any Herculean diſeaſe
<pb facs="tcp:30498:14"/>where the capacity of the ſubject will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the conteſt, and be conformable to the commands of ſuch a diſcipline, I ſhall require to be obſerved. The Patient muſt bear a part, or no good to be expected, there muſt be a conſpiration, conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between the Phyſician, the Patient, and the Medicine againſt the diſeaſe, or the deſign will fail: The Phyſician cannot oure without a good Medicine, the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine cannot cure, except prudently appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Phyſitian in fit Doſes, at due times, with the requiſite circumſtances; and yet neither ſhall prevaile, if the patient be diſobedient, intemperate and careleſs: For if by good medicine you prevaile againſt your diſeaſe, get ground one day and loſe it the next, or ſoon after, by an unfit impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ordering your ſelf, the labour is in vain; as by too often experience we finde it in practiſe, with peeviſh, unruly, imprudent patients, who thinke the taking of the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is ſufficient, let themſelves live at the old rate and cuſtomes which firſt occaſioned the diſeaſe. You muſt not therefore expect theſe medicines to take that effect as is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:30498:14"/>&amp; declared in the enumeration of their vertues &amp; appropriate uſe; if you by an irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular courſe and daily common practiſe in eating, drinking, ſleeping, paſſions of minde, reſt and motion, or other cuſtomes whatever, improper and unfit for the condition of your body and diſtemper, act with a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter motion and repugnancy to the efficacy and vertue of the Medicine, and alſo che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, indulge, and ſtrengthen the diſeaſe. Therefore remember that a duty is required, incumbent upon you, and impute not your miſcarriages, improper, unſeaſonable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient uſe of the means, to the deficiency of the Medicine; and that you make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a chronic, inveterate, radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated diſeaſe, to which you are propenſe by hereditary nature, conſtitution, or conſtant bad cuſtomes; and a ſlight accidental in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity. The former requiring a more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious proſecution, continuance and repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Medicines; if you have been many moneths, perhaps years contracting a diſeaſe you may well allow ſome days for a parting.</p>
            <p>And that theſe Medicines may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a prejudice in their reputation unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly,
<pb facs="tcp:30498:15"/>and for want of knowledge in the proper choice and uſe of them, eſpecially in ſuch caſes and perſons, where a ſubordinate uſe of Medicines is required, for the era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of a contumacious and chronic diſeaſe: ſuch I ſay, who deſire a metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical and exact courſe in the uſe of theſe Medicines, more at large, and peculiar for their complicated diſeaſes and condition of body, then what is expreſt and provided for in this book; I ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their application to me whether by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (if far diſtant) or otherwiſe; give them my advice and directions in the choice and uſe of any Medicine or Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as their particular caſe requires, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true account and relation I ſhall receive of their infirmities, at my dwelling next to the <hi>Blew-Bore</hi> on <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi>-hill, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30498:15"/>
            <head>OF Life, Health, and Sickneſs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the praevious diſpoſition of formation and effiguration of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal matter in the wombe, by the innate ſpirits thereof, the chief actors in vegetation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prepared, fabricated and made ready for animation, the Soul then exerts her power, animates, and gives life; and as ſupreme moderator and governor diſpoſeth and orders all for future conſervation and perfection of operation. The ſeminal Spirits which before were chief and principal in preparation and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brication of this manſion; are now after the ſouls aſſuming the Government, but inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and ſubordinate, immediately acting by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power from the ſoul received, neither can the one act without the other; the ſoul cannot act the body in its operations, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the intervening Spirits: there is ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30498:16"/>great a diſtance between the ſpirituality of a ſoul, and the corporiety of bodies; but the Spirits being of the moſt refined, ſubtile, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latized material ſubſtance, are the fitteſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium of conjunction, conveyance, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce between the Soul and body, nor can the ſpirits act their parts in any Vital operation, but by the energy, command and power derived from the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpirits have their reſidence in every part of the body, as principal aſſiſtants and excitors to the performance of the office, and duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſeveral parts, and are the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proximate immediate agents of the ſoul; and they are preſerved, maintained and ſupplied by the additional ſpirits, extracted from the bodyly aliment daily received.</p>
            <p>There is alſo a ferment or tranſmutative qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity peculiar to each part or office for concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reſulting from the particular nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty and temper of each part; being the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of alteration and tranſmutation, by vertue whereof the food received is digeſted, volatized, and receiving various impreſſions according to the diſpoſition of the ferment of each part by which it paſſeth, until it be fit for aſſimilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the ſubſtance of the body.</p>
            <p>In the vigour and rectitude of theſe ferments and the aforeſaid ſpirits, conſiſts the ſanity and integrity of each member in its office; but the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30498:16"/>diminution, alienation and depravation of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vitiates and imbecillitates the parts, indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and incapacitates them to their office and duties, from whence various morbifick effects are produced, anſwerable to their ſeveral cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the variety of organical parts, in their principal or miniſterial functions.</p>
            <p>Theſe Spirits and ferments are preſerved and maintained in their natural purity and vigour, by a temperate ſweet Air; wholſom and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar dyet, ſeaſonable ſleeping and waking, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and conſtant exerciſe, due evacuations and retentions, tranquillity and eaſe of minde. But theſe irregular, unnatural, diſproportionate or unſutable, in matter, manner, times or order, deſtroyes the regular oeconomy and peaceable Government of the body, raiſeth diſcords, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth and begets morbifick cauſes, abbrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates and ſhortens life. Of which particularly hereafter.</p>
            <p>This I have premiſed as a ground work for the ſuperſtructure intended, and for your preparation and clearer apprehenſion of what ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the following diſcourſe, knowing upon what baſes it is founded.</p>
            <p>The life of man conſiſts in the Conjunction of ſoul and body, mutually embracing each other with the bands of Love and deſire of continued Union, until the incapacity and unfitneſs of the body by its ruinous and decayed condition,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30498:17"/>or other impediments and deficiency enforceth the ſoul to deſertion and departure. Spiritual and Corporeal ſubſtance are now knit and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven one with another, by an extraordinary curious artifice and contrivance, ſo that you can not ſay here is the ſoul &amp; there the body, but ſoul and body are joyntly extended throughout the whole, &amp; in every part there is both ſoul &amp; body: life is the reſult of this connexion; as by the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and attrition of flint &amp; ſteel fire is produced, ſo by the reciprocal contact &amp; conjunction of ſoul &amp; body life is generated, being of a luminous influential nature diradiated through the body from whence vital motions and heat, as the product and concomitants thereof do give a teſtimony of its virtual preſence and efficacious energy: and as the <hi>Ratio formalis</hi> of life is in <hi>lumine;</hi> ſo the vertue, power and emanations of life are manifeſted <hi>in actione,</hi> in operation &amp; acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and although the ſoul cannot by a reflex act in this life, ſee the face of its own being, nor can we ſee it in another, being inviſible a <hi>priori,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed, vailed and hid by the interpoſition of a denſe opacous body, yet we may ſee the back parts and behold what it is in operation and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: and as <hi>Operatio ſequitur eſſe,</hi> according to the axiome; we may judge of the purity, radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and durability of life, by the integrity, ſtrength and conſtancy of its actions and functions: and this integrity or perfection of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30498:17"/>vital operations is that which we call health or ſanity: and it is the free, indiſturbed unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous performance of all the faculties in the recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their duties, being the proſperous ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, mutual enjoyment and happineſs of ſoul and body in their conjunct ſtate.</p>
            <p>The benefit and excellencies of this health is beſt known to thoſe that have loſt it, <hi>Carendo magis quam fruendo, quid valeat cognoſcimus:</hi> you that have it and know not how to prize it, Ile tell you what it is both poſitively, and priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, that you may love it better, put a higher value upon it, and endeavour to preſerve it with a more ſerious and, ſtrict obſervance and tuition.</p>
            <p>Health is that which makes your meat and drink both ſavory and pleaſant, elſe natures injunction of eating and drinking were a hard task and ſlaviſh cuſtome.</p>
            <p>Health is that which makes your bed eaſie, and your ſleep refreſhing, that renews your ſtrength with the riſing Sun, and makes you chearful at the light of another day; tis that which fills up the hollow and uneven places of your Carkaſe, and makes your body plump and comely; tis that which dreſſeth you up in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures richeſt attire, and adorns your face with her choiceſt colours.</p>
            <p>'Tis that which makes exerciſe a ſport, and walking abroad the enjoyment of your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30498:18"/>
            <p>'Tis that which makes fertile and encreaſeth the natural endowments of your minde and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves them long from decay; makes your wit acute, and your memory retentive.</p>
            <p>Tis that which ſupports the fragility of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body, and preſerves the verdure, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and beauty of youth.</p>
            <p>'Tis that which makes the ſoul take delight in her manſion, ſporting her ſelf at the caſements of your eyes.</p>
            <p>'Tis that which makes pleaſure to be pleaſure, and delights delightful; without which you can ſolace your ſelf in nothing of terrene felicityes and enjoyments.</p>
            <p>Having taken a breif ſurvey of natural life in the beſt eſtate, graced and adorned with the ſociety of health and its great attendants; the coucomitant benefits, priviledges and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: now take a view of your ſelf when health hath turn'd its back upon you, and deſerts your company; ſee now how the Scene is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; how you are robd and ſpoyled of your comforts and enjoyments; the want of health makes food to loſe its wonted reliſh, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come diſguſtful and unſavory: the ſtomack now refuſeth to receive its dayly charge, no longer able to perform the task, but deſires a <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> from the office.</p>
            <p>Sleep that was ſtretcht out from evening to the fair bright day, is now broken into pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30498:18"/>and ſubdivided not worth the accounting: the night that before ſeemed ſhort is now too long; and the downy bed preſſeth hard againſt the bones.</p>
            <p>Exerciſe now is toyling, and walking abroad the carrying of a burthen.</p>
            <p>The body that moved ſo light, and readily obeyed the ſteerage of the Pilot; is now over ballac'd with its own weight, and ſlowly tugs as againſt the ſtream.</p>
            <p>Conjugal imbraces are now but the faint off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of love, the ſhaddows, and repreſentations of former kindeneſs.</p>
            <p>The body that had the magnetiſme and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret attraction of ſouls, may now be approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without loſs, or danger of being ſnared and fettered as a bondſlave: the lilly and the roſe that nature planted in the higheſt mount to ſhew the world her pride and glory, is now blaſted, and withered like long blown flowers. The eye that flaſht as lightning, is now like the opacous body of a thick cloude; that rouled from Eaſt to Weſt ſwifter then a Celeſtial orbe, is now tyred and weary but ſtanding ſtill; that penetrated the center of another microcoſme, hath loſt its Planetary influence and is become obtuſe and dull: the hollow ſounding breaſt that echoed to the chanting bird, and warbled forth delightful tunes, now runs diviſions with coughing ſtraines, and pauſes with a deep fetch't
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30498:19"/>ſigh for breath, to repeat thoſe notes again.</p>
            <p>The Veins, thoſe rivulets that ran with vital ſtreams bedewing the adjacent parts with fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full moiſture, is now drunk up with parching heat, or muddied and defiled with an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of excremental humors.</p>
            <p>The want of health converts your houſe into a priſon, and confines you to the narrow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of a chamber, tis that which ſowers the ſweeteſt and moſt beloved injoyments: tis that which diſunites and breaks the league of copartnerſhip between ſoul and body, alienates and makes them at jarrs, diſcompoſeth their harmony, and weary of their wonted, ſweet ſociety.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Prolongation &amp; Abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation of Life.</head>
               <p>MAn Conſiſting of ſoul and body, and this body compounded of <hi>heterogenious</hi> and diſſimilar parts, deſtinated to various actions and offices, and not independent in being and conſervation; will neceſſarily require variety of aſſiſtance and ſupply, proportionable and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their ſeveral purpoſes, faculties, proprieties and temperatures; in matter, manner, times and order; for their maintenance and ſuſtentation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30498:19"/>in the integrity of their actions, offices and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Conſtitutional diſpoſitions and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, peculiarly conſervative of themſelves, reſpectively and conſequently of the whole: And by the Law of nature, (being ſubject to corruption and diſſolution, through the fragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of conſtitutive principles, connexion and fabrication) is bound to obſerve rules, orders and cuſtomes moſt conſonant for preſervation &amp; continuance in being. Now if there be a diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion or unfitneſs, in the matter and <hi>quantum;</hi> or irregularity in the manner times or order of the auxiliary requiſites and conſervatives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what the Law or neceſſity of his nature requires and commands, there ariſeth diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ataxjes and diſorders, the <hi>praeludiums</hi> to ruine and diſſolution.</p>
               <p>And this body being in a continual flux and reflux, converſant in viciſſitudes and variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of oppoſites, diſſimilars, contraries and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, as heat and cold, ſiccity and humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, filling and emptying, reſt and motion, ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and waking, inſpiration and expiration, and the like; could not ſubſiſt amidſt theſe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſubalter nations, if they were not bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and regulated by due order of ſucceſſion to fit and convenient times, that they might not claſh <hi>interfeere</hi> and encroach upon each others privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, due times and proprieties.</p>
               <p>If heat exceeds, the radical moiſture dryes up,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30498:20"/>the ſpirits evaporate, and the body withers.</p>
               <p>If cold, the faculties are torpid and benum'd, the ſpirits being frozen up to a ceſſation from their duties.</p>
               <p>If moiſture prevails, the ſpirits are cloged, ſuffocated and drowned in the chanels of the body.</p>
               <p>If ſiceity and dryneſs, the organical parts are ſtubborne, unpliable and uncapable of their regular motions and due actions, the vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreams being drank up that ſhould irrigate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and ſupple them.</p>
               <p>Were the body alwaies taking in and ſending nothing forth; it would either increaſe to a monſtrous and vaſte magnitude, or fill up, ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and ſtifle the ſoul: were it alwaies in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and emiſſion, the body would waſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and be reduced to nothing.</p>
               <p>Nor is the receiving in of any thing, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and ſatisfactory to the body for its preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but that which is appointed by nature proper and ſutable: nor emiſſion or ejection of any thing, but that which is ſuperfluous and unneceſſary to be retained.</p>
               <p>If ſleep prevailes contrary to the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the body in a lethargic ſoporiferous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity, ſtupefied and ſenſeleſs lies at the gates of death.</p>
               <p>If watching exceeds the limits, tranſgreſſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſteals away the due time for ſleep, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30498:20"/>are debilitated and enervated, the ſpirits tyred, worn out and impoveriſhed.</p>
               <p>If inſpiration were conſtant without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the body would puffe up and be blown like a bladder.</p>
               <p>If expiration were continual, the ſoul and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits would ſoon quit their habitation and come forth.</p>
               <p>If alwaies exerciſed in motion, the body would pine and weare away: if alwaies at reſt, it would corrupt and ſtink.</p>
               <p>There is a rule therefore proportion, meaſure and ſeaſon to be obſerved, in all the requiſite ſupports and auxiliary helps, belonging to our preſervation, and by how much or often, any of theſe neceſſary alternative ſucceſſions are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant and irregular, exceeding the bounds and limits preſcribed by nature, juſtling out the ſucceſſive appointed action duty or cuſtom from its ſeaſonable exerciſe and due execution; by ſo much is the harmony of nature diſturbed, vigour abated and duration ſhortned, by thoſe jarrs, diſcords and encroachments.</p>
               <p>The thwarting and croſſing of nature in any thing ſhe hath enjoyned, either in the ſubſtance or circumſtance, is violence offered to nature, and is deſtructive more or leſs according to the dignity or quality of the thing appointed.</p>
               <p>For nature was not ſo indifferent in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe duties and cuſtomes, that they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30498:21"/>might be done or not done; or ſo careleſs and irregular, to leave them at your pleaſure, when and how, or to be uſed promiſcuouſly and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly without order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the liberty of your will, fancy and occaſions: for as you may ſee in all other creatures exactneſs of rule, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and conſtant order impreſſed upon and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated in their natures, by which they act al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſutable regular and conſtant: you may not imagine ſo choice and exquiſite a peice as man, to be left without a law and rule to guide and ſteer him in the neceſſary actions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, and that he ſhould rove in uncertain, inconſtant, unlimited quantities, times, orders, manners and the like; but is bounded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained upon penalties and forfeitures of being, well being and long being, to the nice and ſtrict obſervance of theſe lawes and cuſtomes neceſſary for the tuition of life and defence of humane frailty.</p>
               <p>As moral good actions are placed in a medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity between two vitious extreams: ſo natural actions and auxiliary requiſites conſervative of life, have their golden meane; digreſſion from which on either ſide leads to ruin and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Too much ſleep or too little; too much meat and drink, or too little to much reſt, or too much motion; too much air, or alwaies cloſe pent up too great excretions or too long retentions too
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30498:21"/>much heat or too much cold; either of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams lead to the gates of death.</p>
               <p>And as nature hath not appointed any thing, or every thing to be food, but this and that; ſo likewiſe not at any time to be received, not in any quantity, after any manner prepared, or in what order you pleaſe, but proportionable, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teable and convenient.</p>
               <p>As there is variety of diſpoſitions and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of minde agreeing with and liking one thing, but diſagreeing reſiſting and diſliking another: ſo is it in the variety of bodies and food: one body is of this conſtitution, temper and appetite; will ſute and agree well with this meat, and diſagree with another: for if all meats were convenient for all bodies to be uſed promiſcuouſly without choice, how comes it to paſs, the antipathy, reſiſtance and abhorrency of ſome bodies againſt ſome particular meats and this not from a fancy and conceipt, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated in the conſtitution; that if it be eaten though unknown, ſhall produce Fluxes, vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſwoonings and ſuch like effects: here is manifeſted the oppoſition, diſagreement and diſtance between this conſtitution and this kind of meat; which being ſo great, that the diſlike and diſcordancy appears preſently: other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreements which are in a lower degree of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, do not manifeſt themſelves immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet they produce ill effects in the body, <hi>plus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30498:22"/>minus, pro viribus,</hi> which diſcover themſelves gradually, at times and ſeaſons and occaſions. If you acknowledge the former you muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of the latter, the reaſon is, <hi>á majori ad mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſleep is appointed by nature, to refreſh the ſpirits and repair loſt ſtrength: ſo the time for ſleep is appointed and limited: not when you pleaſe: the Sun that glorious light was not made for you to ſleep by, nor the night for ſports and revells, but for reſt.</p>
               <p>Nature does not only command what to be done; but when, how much, how long, after what manner, in what order; the modification, Circumſtances and requiſite qualifications, as well as the thing it ſelf, are to be regarded. And therefore by a diligent inquiſition and curious ſpeculation into the workes of nature, you may as much admire the manner of preſervation, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, order, weight and meaſure, regular viciſſitudes alternations and ſucceſſions, as the excellency and contrivance of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in their creation and generation.</p>
               <p>Whatever is appointed by nature as neceſsary for conſervation and ſupport of being though never ſo good, yet if it be unſeaſonable, out of courſe, immoderate in quantity, quality or duration; alters the property and Intention of nature, converts good purpoſes to bad effects.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30498:22"/>
               <p>We ſay every thing is beſt in its own kind; and of continuance in its own Element: and nature is moſt cheerful, vigorous and durable in the courſe and method of her own injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but being put by, thruſt out of her own way, is not of long duration: the birds cannot live in the Sea, nor the fiſh upon the land, nor your nature continue long in an unnatural way againſt her ſelf. Are you compoſed of natural principles, and will you not live conformable to what you are? do you not live by natures aſſiſtance and natural means, and do you think to continue long in a Counter-motion againſt the nature of your Compoſition? they that invert na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures courſe, prepoſterouſly promiſcuouſly &amp; in congruouſly uſing the neceſſary conſervatives of life; not onely are deprived of their benefit, but alſo receive a poſitive hurt, diſordering the conſtant regular motions in the body, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſing the harmonious and ſociable tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments of the parts.</p>
               <p>There is a rule therefore, method, meaſure and ſeaſon, in all the requiſite ſupports and auxiliary helps belonging and neceſſary unto life, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions and cuſtomes whatſoever; which duely obſerved, are of much advantage for the preſervation of the body in its true natural ſtate, vigour and prolongation of being: but other wiſe, a methodically and inordinately uſed, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs natures courſe, uniformity and regularity-
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30498:23"/>of operations, raiſeth unnatural motions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and ceſſations; introduceth diſorders and disjoynes the frame of nature, accelerates and haſtens the diſſolution of the body.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Impediments of long Life.</head>
                  <p>AN infirme, and weak conſtitution from the Wombe derived from tender, imbecile and infirm parents. Irregular and unfit tractation of Infants, whoſe tender bodies are ſoon diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and diſordered by bad Nurſes, their erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious cuſtomes, and the ill proprieties of their milk.</p>
                  <p>Noxious and intemperate Aire.</p>
                  <p>Irregular eating and drinking.</p>
                  <p>Immoderate and unſeaſonable exerciſe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or labour.</p>
                  <p>Too much, or unfit reſt.</p>
                  <p>Sleeping and waking in extreams.</p>
                  <p>Immoderate <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Undue excretion, and retention of Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</p>
                  <p>Inordinate paſſions, and perturbations of mind.</p>
                  <p>All unneceſſary and bad cuſtomes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="precautions">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:30498:23"/>
               <head>Hygiaſtic Precautions, and Rules for the preſervation of Health, and prolongation of life.</head>
               <div n="air" type="section">
                  <head>Of Aire.</head>
                  <p>AIre is ſo neceſſary to life, that without it we cannot ſubſiſt: which ſurrounding us about, and being continually ſuckt and drawn in, muſt needs affect the body with its conditions and properties, and by obſervation you may finde, the body, by the various conſtitutions and changes in the air, to be variouſly affected, well and ill diſpoſed; of which, infirme parts are moſt ſenſible, that they prognoſticate before an alteration come: the minde alſo by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the ſpirits is drawn into conſent, and hath its diſpoſitions and variations: when the Aire is cloſe, thick and moiſt, the ſpirits are more dull heavy and indiſpoſed; but at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Sun, and a ſerene sky, the ſpirits are unfettered, vigorous and active; the minde more cheerful, airy and pleaſant.</p>
                  <p>The Spirits are of an aetherial nature, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30498:24"/>therefore do much ſympathize with the preſent conſtitution, and change of air: for of the air drawn in by the motion of the vital parts, are the vital ſpirits augmented &amp; ſupplied continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, by the peculiar ferment and operation of the heart, therefore the pureneſs of the aire, makes much for the purity of the ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>A groſs impure and noiſome aire, obtunds and deads the ſpirits, makes a ſlow pulſe, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs the pores and hinders ventilation, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates ſuperfluous humors and cauſeth putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
                  <p>A ſerene ſweet thin Aire perfumes and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies an unwholſome body; cheriſheth the heart, makes a lively pulſe, and much encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the vital ſpirits; rarifies and volatizeth a groſs coagulate blood, opens the pores for tranſpiration of putrid and offenſive vapours, acuates and ſharpens the appetite, and helps digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>The beſt aire and moſt agreeable to temperate bodies is in temperate climates, for heat, cold wet and dry: not ſubject to ſudden and violent changes, as in ſome parts of <hi>America</hi> and other Countries very frequent; not groſs and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, infected with putrid vapours and noxious exhalations, from ſtinking ditches, Lakes, Boggs, Carrions, Dunghills, Sinks and Vaults, for which cauſes great Cities, and the adjacent places are not ſo healthful nor the people ſo long liv'd.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:30498:24"/>
                  <p>Change of Aire ſomtimes is very neceſſary for the conſervation of health; the recovery of it declining and loſt: for, temperate bodies by an intemperate aire, ſhall gradually and in time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come intemperate: intemperate bodies, by the contrary intemperate Aire ſhall be reduced to temperature; at leaſt, ſhall conduce much and be very Auxiliary for the reduction. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bodies declining from exact temperature, are beſt preſerved in that Aire oppoſite to their declenſions: as Cholerick, hot and dry bodies, in a moiſt and coole aire; Phlegmatick, cold and moiſt bodies, in a dry and warme Aire.</p>
                  <p>It is not therefore of ſmall moment, in what place you live; and more eſpecially ſuch, who labour of, or are more ſubject to, any pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral infirmity: for the Lungs being of ſo tender a ſubſtance and porous, continually drinking in the aire, is moſt apt to receive impreſſions from it according to the qualities it is pregnant with and infeſted; and many diſeaſes of the breaſt ariſe from this ſole cauſe; and many exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by it and continued: hence it is Aſthmatick Phthiſical and Conſumptive perſons ſhall not be cured in ſome places, but may have cure in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
                  <p>Be cloathed according to the Clemency, ſeaſon and temperature of the Aire, your age, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of body: leane and thin bodies, pervious <hi>(corpora rarae texturae)</hi> and whoſe skin are looſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30498:25"/>and lax; may wear thicker cloathing, becauſe ſuch are more perſpirable, do <hi>magis emittere &amp; tranſpirare;</hi> and are alſo more penetrable and ſubject to injury of the Aire. Fat and fleſhy people, and whoſe bodies are ſolid, firm and hard, are more impenetrable and impervious, and may wear thinner Garments. Infants and children lately cheriſhed in the ſtove of the wombe, being of tender, ſoft bodies and porous, are eaſily expoſed to the prejudice of the Aire, Vigorous youth, and middle age being accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to all weathers, whoſe ſpirits abounding do ſtrongly reſiſt and keep out the aſſaults and injuries of an offenſive Aire, may beſt indure hardſhip. Old age whoſe natural heate is abated, and ſpirits exhauſted, ſtands in need of good defenſatives againſt external cold, and to cheriſh internal heat.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve the ſeaſons and changes of the Aire, and be then moſt careful, for at ſuch times you are in moſt danger to exchange health for ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: hence it is that Spring and Autumne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds moſt with diſeaſes; the Air then aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new qualities oppoſite to its former conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſets new impreſſions upon our bodies, which occaſions the various aeſtuations and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid fermenting of humours, producing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſymptomes according to the variety of their nature, the organical difference, office and conſtitution of the ſeveral parts.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30498:25"/>
                  <p>The Sun being riſen, and the aire clear, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your Chamber-windowes, that the freſh Aire may perfume your Room, and the cloſe Aire and incloſed vapours may go forth.</p>
                  <p>Bad ſmells and putrid vapours being drawn in with the Aire are very injurious to the Lungs and vital parts; contaminating the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and impreſſing upon the ferment of thoſe parts their tetrid nature, are oftentimes the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of a Conſumption; and if the Lungs be weak and infirme, are more apt to receive the prejudice then others. But fragrant ſmells re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and chear the vital Spirits, and are very wholſome, breathing forth the vertue of thoſe things from whence they do proceed.</p>
                  <p>Be not late abroad, nor very early; before Sun riſing and after ſetting the Aire is not ſo good; being infeſted with noxious vapours, until the radient influence of the Sun diſpells and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies: and thoſe whoſe cuſtome it is to be often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proad at ſuch times, are moſt frequently moleſted with Rheumes, &amp; Rheumatic diſeaſes, which their declining years will more evidently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the prejudice. Likewiſe in moiſt, foggy, dark weather, tis better being within then abroad; and if it be a cool ſeaſon, good fires &amp; fragrant fumes are then both pleaſant &amp; very wholeſom. Be frequent abroad in the fields when a clear sky invites you forth, and let the freſh Aire fan you with its ſweet breath; but more eſpecially in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30498:26"/>the morning; the Aire is ſofter and more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant then your bed, and ſure I am, far more wholſome.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Temperie Coeli corpuſque Animuſque juvatur</p>
                     <bibl>Ovid</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="food and drink" type="section">
                  <head>Meat and Drink.</head>
                  <p>Eſteem temperance and regularity in eating and drinking as a great preſervative of health, not a Leſſian dyet to pine and enſeeble the body, but moderate in quantity propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the ſtomack, agreeable in the firſt and ſecond qualities, ſeaſonable as to times and order. The contrary irregular practice hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and ſhortned the lives of many. <hi>Plures gula quam gladius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For quantity, your own ſtomack muſt meaſure to you what is convenient; which is a certain rule of proportion, if you obſerve not to eat to a ſatiety and fullneſs, but deſiſt with an appetite, being refreſhed light and cheerfull, not dulled heavy and indiſpoſed to operation and action, either of mind or body.</p>
                  <p>A ſet quantity or meaſure of meat and drink, cannot be preſcribed as a general rule and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30498:26"/>for all to follow, in regard of the variety and great difference of perſons, in Conſtitution, age, ſtrength of nature, condition of life, and infirmities, that what is convenient for one, is too much for another, and too little for a third; the ſtrong and healthy cannot conforme to the ſickly weak and infirme in quantity, nor the labouring man to the ſedentary and ſtudious, or the idle: therefore every ſtomack is to be its own judge: and every one ought to moderate themſelves by the cautions before mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Indulge not to the cravings of an irrationall ſenſitive appetite, but allow ſuch a ſupply of daily food, as will ſupport and maintain bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrength and not over-load it: thereby the ſpirits will be vigorous and active, humors at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuated and abated, Crudities and obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons prevented, many infirmities checkt and kept under, the ſenſes long preſerved in their integrity, the ſtomack clean, the appetite ſharp; and digeſtion good. But by the ſurpluſage and over-charge, the ſtomachical ferment is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid and its inciſive penetrative faculty obtun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the appetite and digeſtion abated, the ſtomack nauſeating, fluctuating, and belching with crudities; from whence Gripes, Fluxes and Feavers: the ſpirits clogged, dull and ſomnolent; by their indiſpoſition and inactivity humors ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, degenerate, incraſſate, obſtructs; from whence various ſymptomes and depraved effects
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30498:27"/>throughout the body, debilitating and decaying the fenſes, enervating and ſtealing away the ſtrength of the body, by defrauding it of good nutriment, haſtning old age, and ſhortning Life.</p>
                  <p>In Winter you may eate more freely, the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient external cold compreſſeth and unites the ſpirits, drives them to the center and fortifyes the ſtomack: but in Summer the ſpirits are dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, exhauſted and drawn forth by the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal heat opening the pores; wherefore the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite is not ſo ſharp, nor digeſtion ſo quick. And the Rule is true, though heate be not the principal cauſe of concoction, yet it is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary agent, excitor and cooperator.</p>
                  <p>For the quality of dyet, make choice of ſuch for the moſt part as is commended to you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for that conſtitution you are of, as you will finde preſcribed in the ſeveral tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments following. But withal obſerve, what is moſt agreeing and diſagreeing to your peculiar nature and individual propriety; what is moſt deſired by your ſtomack and beſt digeſted, is a good guide in the choice of meate and drink.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paulo peior ſed ſuavior cibus &amp; potus, meliori, at ingrato praferendus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Change your dyet according to the ſeaſons of the year, the variation of your temperament, and inclination to this or that diſtemper: in Winter more meate and leſs drink; in ſummer leſs meate and more liquids:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30498:27"/>in hot weather a cooling diet, in cold weather that which is warme and heating: in ſummer meats boiled, in winter roſted: a hot and dry body muſt have a cooling and moiſt diet; a cold and moiſt body, a hot and dry diet: tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate bodies are preſerved by temperate things and their like; diſtempered bodies are rectified and reduced by their contraries and diſſimilar.</p>
                  <p>The more ſimple and ſingle your diet is, the better and more wholeſome: but if your ſtomack muſt have variety, let it be at ſeveral meals, and ſo you may pleaſe your pallate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice: accuſtome not your ſelf to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies and compound diſhes, the <hi>heterogenity</hi> of their nature, begets a diſcordant ſermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſtomack, troubling concoction, from whence eructations, nauſeous belchings, and offenſive riſings in the throat. <q>Quo ſimplicior vict us ratio eo melior. <bibl>Aphor.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of all meat, fleſh affords the moſt nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the ſtrongeſt.</p>
                  <p>If your diet ſometimes be not ſo good and proper for you in the quality, make amends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the quantity and eat the leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Of all ſauces a good ſtomack is the beſt; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f you muſt have other, let it be <hi>acide</hi> ſharp or biting.</p>
                  <p>Accuſtome ſtrong ſtomacks to ſtrong meats; the weaker to lighter of digeſtion: very light meats in ſtrong ſtomacks are ſoon digeſted, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30498:28"/>withall parched and corrupted, and turn to a bitter and cholerick juce; ſolid hard meats in weak ſtomacks lye long and heavy, and paſſe away crude and indigeſted.</p>
                  <p>Meats in reſpect of their facility and difficulty in digeſtion are tearmed heavy and light.</p>
                  <p>Heavy meats be ſuch as are more dry, hard, ſolid and denſe, groſſe, courſe and tough, or over moiſt ſlimy and cold: requiring a longer time in fermentation, volatization and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, before they be fit to paſſe off the ſtomack.</p>
                  <p>And they are either ſo in their nature: as all old fleſh, bull beef and oxe, brawn, pork, veniſon, hare, gooſe, duck, ſwan, crane, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, heron and moſt water fowle: Eeles, lobſter lampreys, tench, ſtockfiſh: beanes, peaſe when they be ſomething old; brown bread, barly and Rye bread: alſo ſome parts are of harder di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion then other; as brains, hearts, livers (except of tame fowl, birds, and ſome very young fleſh) milts, kidneys, skin.</p>
                  <p>Meat made heavy (or made worſe then in their own nature) by preparation, keeping and dreſſing, as dryed, fryed and broiled meats; meats long ſalted and kept, as bacon, hang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d beef, and long powdered, old ling, ſalt cod, haberdine, pickled herrings red herrings, pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſcallops; ſturgion, ſalt ſalmon, old cheeſe, hard eggs, toſted cheeſe, toſted bread eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30498:28"/>if it be ſcorched; cruſts, pye cruſt, bread not well baked, unleavened: meats over baked, hard and dry; long kept, meats roſted dry, or ſcorched.</p>
                  <p>Light meats and of quicker digeſtion, be ſuch as are more ſoft and tender, rare as it is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to denſity, therefore ſooner penetrated by the ſtomachicall ferment; ſucculent, volatile, ſoon fermenting and yeilding to digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>As young tender fleſh: veal, young mutton, lamb, kid, pullet, capon, chicken, conies, turky, pheaſant, patridge, plover, woodcock ſnite, heath cocks, railes, ſmall birds: whiting, ſmelt, biſter, flownder, ſoles, plaiſe, thornback, maids, turbut, ſhrimps, prawnes, trout, carp, pike, bream, perch, roches, daces, loches: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere eggs, milk, wheat bread, white, light, and well baked; alſo oaten bread well made: and theſe may be divided into two ſorts; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, meats very light as rere eggs, ſucking rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, chickens, whitings: and meats indifferent light, as mutton lambe, veale.</p>
                  <p>Very light meats are ſoon digeſted, apt to be corrupted; breeds tender and effeminate bodies, ſoft and looſe fleſh eaſily loſt: ſolid ſtrong meats are ſlower in digeſtion, not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted, ſlow in diſtribution, makes ſtrong bodies firm hard fleſh and durable.</p>
                  <p>Uſe not meats that hath any quality in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame; as very ſalt, very hot, ſower, binding
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30498:29"/>or the like: but keep to thoſe that are mode rate.</p>
                  <p>Let your bread be of wheat, leavened, wel kneaded and baked, light and white; which you may eat new, but not hot; nor ſtaler then two days old, and chuſe the crumb, rather then the cruſt.</p>
                  <p>Seaſonings of meat are uſed either as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives to keep them from putrefaction and decay; or as correctives, to alter and change ſome ill quality, and promote digeſtion; or for delight to gratify the pallate; as ſugar, ſalt, vinegar, muſtard, peper, cloves and other ſpices.</p>
                  <p>Meat moderately ſalted, having time to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ferment, volatize, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er the crude qualities, is better and wholeſomer then freſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> but to eat ſalt at the table is not ſo good, if the condition of the meat be ſuch as to allow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> praevious digeſtion and ſeaſoning. Salt is grateful to the pallate and ſtomack, excites the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, concocts crude flegmatick matter that lies upon the ſtomack, hinders putrefaction and is abſterſive: but immoderately uſed, corrodes and frets, cauſeth itching and breakings out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> very bad for thin lean bodyes, it heats and dryes the blood and radical moiſture,</p>
                  <p>Sugar in a temperate clean body, moderately uſed nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſheth and is good, but in a ſoul body is ſoon corrupted, degenerates and makes the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30498:29"/>body more impure; turns to choler and inflames cholerick hot bodies. The freequent and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate uſe in any obtunds and abates the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, cauſeth putrid humors and makes an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome body.</p>
                  <p>Vinegar and ſower juces as of lemmon, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juce and the like; procure appetite and help the ſtomack in digeſtion of groſſer meats: but the immoderate and frequent uſe, cooles, dries, conſtringeth and bindes the body, hurtful to the nerves and nervous parts; very bad for women, and thoſe that are ſubject to the Gout, Aſthmaes and ſtoppings in the breaſt, or in other parts, and for lean dry bodies.</p>
                  <p>Muſtard quickens the appetite, warmes the ſtomack, dries up ſuperfluous moiſture, helps the ſtomack in digeſting hard meats, opens ſtoppings in the breaſt and head.</p>
                  <p>Mace, ginger, nutmeg, peper, and cloves, they help a cold ſtomack, comfort the heart and brain, refreſh the ſpirits by their aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical odour, are grateful upon the pallate, and very acceptable to phlegmatick cold bodies.</p>
                  <p>In the uſe of the forementioned, I ſhall give this caution: that young ſtomacks, and ſtrong healthy bodies which need not a ſpur to their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, nor a help to digeſtion, that they frequent not the uſe of theſe ſeaſonings and ſauces; but reſerve them for age; deficiency of ſtomack and other infirmities; for if you accuſtome your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30498:30"/>ſelf to them in youth and ſtrength, to pleaſe your pallate and intice your ſtomack there being no need; when the condition of your body does require them, you ſhall not finde that benefit and aſſiſtance from them, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you might have expected and received, had you forborn the uſe of them when it was not neceſſary.</p>
                  <p>When you come to Meate, leave your care and buſineſs, but bring in your friend, and be as merry as you can, mirth and good company is a great help to a dull ſtomack both for appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>Eate not preſently after exerciſe, and when you are hot; but forbear until the ſpirits be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired and ſetled in their ſtations.</p>
                  <p>Eat not haſtily but chew your meat well, tis a good preparation for concoction, and your ſtomack will more eaſily and ſooner di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt it; but if it be half chewed the ſtomack muſthave the labour to chew it over again with its inciſive ferment.</p>
                  <p>Liquid meats ſoluble and lighter of digeſtion eate firſt; the more ſolid laſt, and that which hath any aſtriction.</p>
                  <p>Drink a little and oft at meat, to macerate and digeſt, eſpecially if your meat be dry and ſolid, and to help diſtribution of aliment; but great draughts cauſeth fluctuations.</p>
                  <p>To ſtand or walk ſoftly after meat is good;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30498:30"/>the ſtomack then being diſtended, is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of any part, which ſitting does not ſo well avoid: but haſty motion opens the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the ſtomack, precipitates and vitiates digeſtion.</p>
                  <p>Forbear reading, writing, ſtudy or ſerious cogitations for two hours after meat; elſe you draw off from the ſtomack, abate the ſtrength of digeſtion, and injure the brain.</p>
                  <p>Omit a meale ſometimes, it acuates and ſharpens the ſtomack, concocts crudities, and makes the next meale reliſh better,</p>
                  <p>Eate no late ſuppers, nor variety at once; a good ſtomack may endure it for a while, but the weaker is more ſenſible of the injury, the beſt is prejudiced in time.</p>
                  <p>Keep a ſufficient diſtance between your times of eating, that you charge not the ſtomack with a new ſupply before the former be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted and paſſed away: and in keeping ſuch a diſtance, your ſtomack will be very fit and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive the next meale, the former being wrought off perfectly; no ſemidigeſted crude matter remaining to commix with the next food: and that is one cheif cauſe of crudities and a foule ſtomack, when a new load is caſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the former be gon off, which begets much excrements, not much aliment, clogs the body and procures diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>The ſtomack that is empty, receives, cloſeth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30498:31"/>and embraceth food with delight, will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſharp in digeſtion, and the body will attract and ſuck the aliment ſtrongly, each part as it paſſeth along will perform its office readily and ſufficiently; which they will not do if often cloyed with depraved and indigeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aliment, but ſlowly and with reluctancy; for although they do not act by reaſon, yet they have a natural inſtinct or endowment, to diſcern their proper and fit object.</p>
                  <p>Drink for neceſſity, not for bad fellowſhip, eſpecially ſoon after meate, which hinders the due fermentation of the ſtomack and waſheth down before digeſtion be finiſhed: but after the firſt concoction, if you have a hot ſtomack, a dry or coſtive body, you may drink more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then others: or if thirſt importunes you at any time, to ſatisfie with a moderate draught is better then to forbear. Accuſtome youth and ſtrong ſtomacks to ſmall drink, but ſtronger drink and wine to the infirm and aged: it cheers the ſpirits, quickens the appetite, and helps di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion.</p>
                  <p>For corpulent groſs and fat bodies, thin hungry abſterſive penetracting wines.</p>
                  <p>For lean thin bodies, black, red and yellow wines, ſweet full bodied and fragrant, are more fit and agreeable.</p>
                  <p>For Drink whether it be wholeſomer warmed then cold; is much controverted, ſome ſtifly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30498:31"/>contending for the one, and ſome for the other: I ſhall rather chuſe the middle way with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation and diſtinction; then impoſe it upon all as a rule to be obſerved under the penalty of forfeiting their health, the obſervation of the one or the other.</p>
                  <p>There are three ſorts of perſons; one cannot drink cold Beer, the other cannot drink warm; the third, either: You that cannot drink cold Beer, to you it is hurtful, cools the ſtomack and checks it much: therefore keep to warm drink as a wholeſome cuſtome: you that cannot drink warm Beer, that is, findes no refreſhment, nor thirſt ſatisfied by it, you may drink it cold, nor is it injurious to you: you that are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and can drink either; drink yours cold, when you cannot have it warmed.</p>
                  <p>That warm Drink is no bad cuſtome, but, agreeable to nature in the generalitie; firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it comes the neareſt to the natural temper of the body, and <hi>ſimilia ſimilibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantur;</hi> every thing is preſerved by its like, and deſtroyed by its contrary: Secondly, heat though I do not hold it the principal agent in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, yet it does excite, is auxiliary and a neceſſary concomitant of a good digeſtion, <hi>ut ſignum &amp; cauſa.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Omne frigus per ſe, &amp; pro viribus diſtruit;</hi> Cold in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and according to the graduation of its power, extinguiſheth natural heat and is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30498:32"/>but <hi>per accidens</hi> and as it is in <hi>gradu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſo,</hi> it may comtemperate, allay, and refreſh, where heat abounds, and is exalted.</p>
                  <p>Therefore as there is varietie of Pallates and Stomacks, likeing and agreeing beſt with ſuch kind of meats and drinks, which to others are utterly diſguſtful, diſagreeing and injurious though good in themſelves: ſo is it in Drink warmed or cold, what one finds a benefit in, the other receives a prejudice; at leaſt does not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd that ſatisfaction and refreſhment, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a quallification; becauſe of the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tempers, particular appetitions and <hi>idioſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical</hi> proprieties of ſeveral bodies, one thing will not agree with all: Therefore he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not drink warm, let him take it cold, and it is well to him; but he that drinks it warm does better.</p>
                  <p>Which is to be underſtood in Winter, when the extremity of cold hath congelated and fixed the ſpirits of the Liquor in a torpid inactivitie; but by a gentle warmth are unfettered, volatile and brisk; whereby the drink is more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and grateful to the ſtomacks fermenting heat, being ſo prepared, then to be made ſo by it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="movement and rest" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30498:32"/>
                  <head>Motion and Reſt.</head>
                  <p>EXerciſe often, in the morning chiefly, with an emptie ſtomack alwayes; and after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cremental evacuation if you can procure it.</p>
                  <p>Exerciſe rowſeth dull inactive ſpirits, gives ventilation, opens obſtructions by the motion attenuation and penetration of the ſubtile ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, agitates and volatiſeth feculent fixed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding humours, concocts and abates ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous moiſture, increaſeth natural heat, promotes concoction, diſtribution and conveyance of ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through the narrow Channels and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages unto the ſeveral parts of the body; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures excremental evacuations, ſtrengthens all the Members, and preſerves Nature in her vigour.</p>
                  <p>Vary exerciſe according to the condition of your body and ſeaſon of the year: the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Phlegmatic bodies, in cold weather, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſtronger and ſwifter motions: Choleric bodies, weak, and the Summer ſeaſon, more mild and gentle.</p>
                  <p>Be not violent in exerciſe, nor continue it longer beyond a pleaſure; but deſiſt with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, not a laſſitude and wearineſs.</p>
                  <p>Put on ſome looſe garment, until your body be cool and ſetled in its natural heat and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30498:33"/>the pores being opened by exerciſe, the cold is more apt to enter, from whence a greater prejudice then you could expect benefit from your labour.</p>
                  <p>Fly idleneſs and a ſedentarie life, for want of due action and motion, the body like ſtanding waters, degenerates, corrupts and decayes.</p>
                  <q>Ignavia corpus hebetat, labor firmat.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="sleep" type="section">
                  <head>Sleep and Watching.</head>
                  <p>MOderate ſleep refreſheth the ſpirits, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth natural heat, helps concoction, gives ſtrength to the body, pacifies anger and calmes the ſpirits, gives a relaxation to a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled mind.</p>
                  <p>Immoderate ſleep dulls the ſpirits, injurious to a good wit and memory, fills the head with ſuperfluous moiſture and clouds the brain; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains excrements beyond their due time to be voided, and infects the body with their noxious fumes and vapours, an enemy to beauty.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Turpis qui alto ſole ſemiſomnis jacet,</l>
                     <l>Cujus vigilia medio die incipit.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Sen.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Go early to ſleep (not with a full ſtomack) and early from ſleep; that you may riſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30498:33"/>freſhed lively and active, not dulled and ſtupid.</p>
                  <p>When you lay by your Clothes, lay aſide alſo your buſineſs care and thoughts, and let not a wandring phanſie prevent your reſt.</p>
                  <p>Let your bed be ſoft, but not to ſink in, which ſuckes from the body, exhauſts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires ſtrength: a Quile upon a Featherbed, is both eaſie and wholeſome.</p>
                  <p>Avoid day ſleeps as a bad cuſtome; chiefly fat and corpulent bodies: but if your ſpirits be tired with much buſineſs and care, or by reaſon of old age, debilitie of nature, extream hot wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, labour or the like that diſſipates the ſpirits; then a moderate ſleep reſtores the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and is a good refreſhment; but rather take it ſitting then lying down.</p>
                  <p>Night watching and late ſitting up, tires and waſtes the animal ſpirits, by keeping them too long upon duty, debilitates nature, changeth the freſh flower of youth, heats the body, dryes, and exaſperates Choler; in time extinguiſheth natural heat, breeds Rhumes and Crudities; moſt injurious to thin leane bodies.</p>
                  <q>Quod caret alterna requie durabile non eſt.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="evacuation" type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30498:34"/>
                  <head>Evacuation and Retention.</head>
                  <p>UNder this Head is compriſed excretions by Stool, Urine, monethly Purgations, <hi>Venus,</hi> by the Pores, pallate Noſe and Ears: of which the former are of the greateſt concernment, and ſpecial care to be had of them.</p>
                  <p>Excremental evacuations are various pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the ſeveral concoctions; conveyed out by ſeveral Channels and Vents: which duly evacuated are no ſmall helps to the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of health, and are the effects of a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and regular body.</p>
                  <p>The retention of them beyond due time, argue diſtemperature of parts, or irregular li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and brings much detriment to the body, by their noxious Fumes and putrid Vapours, that might infect, corrupt, and diſturb the body.</p>
                  <p>Immoderate evacuations cauſeth weakneſs debilitie of nature by exhauſtion, and procures ſeveral diſeaſes, Cachexies, Conſumptions, Dropſies, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To keep the body ſoluble is very good, that at leaſt once a day you may not miſs to have a ſtool; elſe the Faeces are hardned, the body heated, the ſtomack moleſted, the appetite not ſo good, the head heavy, dull and ſometimes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30498:34"/>pained; ſome groſſer matter which ſhould go away by ſeige, is brought by the Urinarie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, occaſioning obſtructions, all which are very injurious and deſtructive to health.</p>
                  <p>Seaſonable and moderate <hi>Venus,</hi> alleviates na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and helps concoction.</p>
                  <p>Immoderate, exhauſts the ſtrength by effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſpirits, exſiccates and dries the body, hurts the brain and nerves, cauſeth tremblings, dulls the ſight, debilitates all the faculties, haſtens old age, and ſhortens life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cibovel potu repletis, ſuperfluè evacuatis, five exercitatis coitus interdicitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tempus optimum eſt mane, &amp; poſt dormias.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hyeme &amp; vere frequentius permittitur, aeſtate parciſſimè.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Juvines ſanguinei &amp; pituitoſi liberalius, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Melancholici, parciſſimè bilioſi, Senes, ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciati.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mares plus quam faeminas laedit, &amp; qui erecti ſolent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="precautions">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:30498:35"/>
               <head>Hygiaſtic Praecautions and Rules Appropriate to the ſeveral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of bodies, with their diag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtic ſignes.</head>
               <p>THE Sanguine is moderately hot and moiſt, hath a lively pulſe, vigorous actions, of colour freſh or roſie, for habite of body ſoft, fleſhy or moderately fat; of a pleaſant mind and good diſpoſition (except caſualties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities alter to the contrary.</p>
               <p>The Sanguine conſtitution being the beſt and moſt temperate, ought to be preſerved in that ſtate from degeneration and intemperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſions: which is performed by a due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of diet, Air Exerciſe and Reſt, Sleep and Watching, voiding and retaining of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and paſſions of the mind: for any of theſe, irregular unſutable, or unnatural of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, will alter and change the beſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered body, into ſome other conſtitution of intemperature anſwerable to their cauſes as the intemperate Air of a hot climate, or ſeaſon not regarded; violent exerciſe, nightwatchings, &amp;c. Introduceth a depraved alteration and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation of the blood.</p>
               <p>For the quality of your diet, let it be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30498:35"/>for temperate bodies muſt uſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate meats, and diſtempered bodies their contraries: therefore keep within this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude generally and for the moſt part, from meats temperate, to meats hot, cold, dry or moiſt in the firſt degree incluſive, thoſe will ſute well with your temperament: Such are Mutton, Cow-beife or Heifer, Pork, Veale, Lamb, Rabbit, Capon, Hen, Pullet, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky, Pheſant, Partridge, Carrots, Turnips, Skirrits, Sparagus.</p>
               <p>For quantity, times and order in eating and drinking; for Aire, Exerciſe and Sleep, conſonant and moſt agreeable to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution are to be ſought in the general Hygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick Rules before mentioned, which are moſt proper and applicable to this complexion; as being the common ſtandard to meaſure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by; and how far others vary from this temperament, by ſo much are they to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted intemperate, and do therefore require ſome particular Rules differing from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, becauſe intemperate conſtitutions and temperate are not be governed by the ſame ſtrictneſs of law, but muſt have ſome allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and exceptions, which ſhall be obſerved in the particular conſtitutions following.</p>
               <div type="constitution">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:30498:36"/>
                  <head>Phlegmatick Conſtitution.</head>
                  <p>THe Phlegmatick perſon is more cool and moiſt, not ſo lively, quick, ſharp and acute as the ſanguine: for habit of body corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fat or fleſhy; the Veines ſmall and hid; a ſlow pulſe; prone to ſleep and eaſe, by cold things prejudiced, by hot things benefitted; incident to cold and Phlegmatick diſtempers, (which are to be underſtood, if cuſtoms caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or infirmities induce not the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Meats agreeable and convenient for this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament, are ſuch as be temperate and ſuch as be hot in the firſt and ſecond degree; not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver moiſt, but potencially drying if heat be wanting: as young Beef powdered, Mutton, Veniſon, Hare, Turkey, Hen, Capon, Pidgeon, Turtle, Black-birds, Feldifars, ſmall Birds, ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Puffins, Artichoaks, Parſnips, Potatoes, pickled Oyſters, Anchovies.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Bacon, Haberdine, old Ling, ſalt Cod, pickled Herrings or dryed, pickled ſcallops, and ſuch like ſavory ſeaſoned meats, this temperament will admit of, if the ſtomack be ſtrong enough to digeſt them. And for the more ſecurity take a glaſs of Sack after.</p>
                  <p>Refuſe Lambe, Kid, freſh Pork, Pig, Gooſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30498:36"/>Duck, and water Fowl, being over moiſt and clogging a Phlegmatick ſtomack. But if your appetite much deſires any of theſe, let them be down roaſted: alſo Eeles, Lampreys, freſh Herrings, Makarel, Lobſter freſh Salmon, Barbel, freſh Sturgeon, Tench, are injurious, and moſt freſh fiſh, yet leſs prejudicial if you drink wine with them.</p>
                  <p>Let your dyet be warm meats, oftener roaſt, then boyled.</p>
                  <p>Butter, Oyle and Honey is very wholſome.</p>
                  <p>Muſtard, Salt and Spices, are good for your uſe, eſpecially with meats of ſlow digeſtion, and that abound with much moiſture.</p>
                  <p>Refuſe Milk, and milk meats, Curds, new Cheeſe, Butter milk and Whey.</p>
                  <p>Olives, Capers, Broom-buds, Sampire are good ſauce, alſo Garlick, Onions, Leeks, in broths, ſeaſonings or ſawces, for a relliſh, but not raw.</p>
                  <p>Refrain cold hearbs and ſallads, as Lettice, Purſlan, Violet leaves; except Sorrel which although cold, yet a dryer and ſharpner of the appetite: but uſe Mint, Sage, Roſmary, Time, Marjerome, Parſley, Pennyroyal and ſuch hot hearbs.</p>
                  <p>Abſtain from raw fruits, Apples, Pears, Plumms, Cucumbers, Mellons, Pumpions, &amp;c. But you may eat Walnuts, Filbirds, Almonds blanched, Cheſtnuts fiftick nuts, Dates, Figs, Raiſins.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:30498:37"/>
                  <p>Drink ſtrong bear more frequently then ſmall and ſometimes Sack. Not French wine if you be Rheumatick.</p>
                  <p>Indulge not your ſelf in lying long in bed, or afternoon ſleeps, too much reſt and eaſe, they dull the ſpirits, increaſe flegm and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous moiſture.</p>
                  <p>Frequent exerciſe and moderate abſtinence in meat and drink, are great preſervatives of your health.</p>
                  <p>Chuſe a warm air and dry ſoil remote from Waters the beſt place for your abode.</p>
                  <p>Hot Baths are profitable, ſeaſonable and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate <hi>Venus</hi> a friend: the former cheriſheth the ſpirits opens obſtructions and dryes up ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous moiſture: the latter ſufcitates and raiſeth the ſpirits, alleviates and helps Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>If the ſmoaking of Tobacco be good for any, the Phlegmatick may beſt challenge the uſe of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="constitution">
                  <head>Cholerick Conſtitution.</head>
                  <p>THe Cholerick perſon is hot and dry, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and precipitate in action; froward, haſty and angry; lean of body and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: the Veines bigg, a hard pulſe, and quick: of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30498:37"/>colour pale, ſwarthy or yellowiſh; the hair criſp or curled; propenſe to waking and ſhort ſleeps; ſubject to Tertain Fevers.</p>
                  <q>Ad venerem proclivior, &amp; cito ſatiatus.</q>
                  <p>Uſe a cool and moiſtning diet, moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently boyled meats rather then roſt or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; but fryed or broiled meats never.</p>
                  <p>Eat brothes often made with cooling hearbs; Rice-milk, Cock-broth, or Barly broths with Raſins Currants and Prunes.</p>
                  <p>For fleſh, chuſe young tender and jucy, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate or cooling; as young Beef, Veal, Motton, Lamb, Kid, Pork, Conies, Green-geeſe, Turky, Capon, Chickens.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve fiſh days as good dyet: and then you may eate freſh Salmon, Sturgeon, Lobſter, freſh Herrings, Crabs, Prauns, freſh God, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Thornback, Soles, Plaiſe, Whiring, Smelt, Perwincle, Oiſters, Pike, Trout, Tench, and all freſh fiſh, Eeles not excepted which are very unwholſome to others.</p>
                  <p>Milk and milk meats are pleaſant and good, as Cuſtard, White-pots, new Cheeſe freſh Cheeſe and Cream.</p>
                  <p>For your ſauces uſe Verjuce, Vinegar, Sorrel Orange, Lemmon, Apples, Goosberies Currans: Prunes, pickled Cucumbers: as boiled Veale and Green-ſauce, roſt Veal and Orange, holled
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30498:38"/>Mutton, with Verjuce and its own juce; roſt Mutton and Lemmon or Cucumbers; green Geeſe and Goosberries; Stubble gooſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Pigg and Currants; Pork and Green-ſauce; boiled Chickens with Goosberries or Sorrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops; Calves feet ſtewed with Currans and Prunes: and your meat thus cook'd is both food and Phyſick.</p>
                  <p>Take a lawful freedome and pleaſe your ſelf with theſe fruits. Citrons, Pomegranats, Limes, Oranges, Lemmons, Quince, Pearmains, Pippins, red Cherries, Mulberies, Grapes, Damſins, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, Prunellaes, Reſpaſs, Currans, Barberies, Strawberries: they cool and quench thirſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate and aſwage Choler, and give a great refreſhment to the parched ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>Eat ſallads of Lettuce, Sorrel, Purſlane Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and Violet leaves; they are medicamental aliment.</p>
                  <p>Butter milk, Whey and Sider allays preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat, checks the effrenation of raging Choler, and are like water to fire.</p>
                  <p>Refuſe the fat and brown outſide of meat: alſo the cruſt of bread: Butter and Oyle adds fuel to the fire: Sugar and Honey hath alliance and friendſhip with Choller, being ſoon aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milated and converted into its nature.</p>
                  <p>Muſtard Salt and Spices exaſperates Cholet and makes it more fierce and biting; Vinegar checks it.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:30498:38"/>
                  <p>Avoid wine, ſpirits, and ſtrong liquors; they agitate Choller, and rouzeth up a ſleeping ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
                  <p>Faſt not but ſatisfie the ſtomack when it vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates and calls for meat; biting Choller muſt have ſomething to feed on, or it will prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the body.</p>
                  <p>Cheriſh and indulge ſleep, it cools and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens, but let it not exceed in length, which puts nature by her due times for neceſſary eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations.</p>
                  <p>Uſe little and gentle exerciſe; be not labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or toyling, but take your eaſe avoid violent motion, it fires the ſpirits and enrageth choler.</p>
                  <p>Frequent <hi>Venus</hi> is moſt pernicious.</p>
                  <p>Cold bathes is profitable and refreſheth much, by cooling the blood allaying the ſpirits concentring them.</p>
                  <p>Banniſh anger immoderate care, peeviſhneſs and fretting which diſcompoſeth the ſpirits heats and waſts them, angments Choller, dryes the body and haſtens old age.</p>
                  <p>Refrain Tobacco as an injurious cuſtome, it exaſperates Choler, by heating, drying, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating dulcid Phlegme which contemperates bridles and checks the fury of acrid, ſharp bili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="constitution">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:30498:39"/>
                  <head>Melancholy Complexion</head>
                  <p>THe Melancholy perſon, naturally ſo from the firſt principles is cold and dry: but a Melancholy temperament, acquired by Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Cuſtomes and Accidents, by Degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and admixture of other humors aduſt, is hot and dry: which make the ſigns and ſymptoms of Melancholy to be different and various, and a difference is to be made in dyet and cuſtoms.</p>
                  <p>The common ſymptoms are a pale, black, or high Sanguine colour; given to be watchful, ſad, ſolitary, and ſuddain laughter; a flow pulſe, troubleſome ſleeps and dreams.</p>
                  <p>Cold Melancholy hath milde ſymptomes; if hot and aduſt, the effects are more churliſh and furious.</p>
                  <p>For cold Melancholly, let the dyet be hot and moiſt: for the hot Melancholy perſon, let dyet be cooling and moiſt: in both let their meats be of light digeſtion, affording good nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment and not windy: as Mutton, Lamb, Veal, Capon, Chicken, Partridge, Pheſant, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Abſtain from Veniſon, Bull-beef or Ox, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Beef or long ſalted, Goats-fleſh, Hare, Bacon, Gooſe, Duck, Swan, Crane, Heron, Bittor and moſt water fowl: Peacock, Quaile, Blackbirds, Pidgeon; Red Herrings, ſalt Cod, Ling, Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30498:39"/>pickled Scallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and ſalt Fiſh: dryed Meats, fryed or broiled, old Cheeſe, Beanes, Peaſe, Cabbage, Coleworts, Rye Bread, and all meats hard of digeſtion or windy.</p>
                  <p>Capers, Broom buds and Sampire are good ſauce, they open Obſtructions of the Liver and Spleen.</p>
                  <p>Muſtard and Vinegar bad, and all ſower ſauces, they make Melancholy more contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and fixed.</p>
                  <p>Spices not good, if the perſon be hot, they cauſe aduſtion.</p>
                  <p>Uſe Borrage, Bugloſs, Endive, Succory, Baume Fumiterry, Lettuce, Marigold flowers, Violets, Clove-giliflowers, Saffron, they alter and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the humor, and chear the ſpirits.</p>
                  <p>Uſe Barly brothes with Prunes, Raiſins and Currans. If Melancholy be aduſt, and your body hot and coſtive, eat Pippins Permains, Cherries, Reſpaſs, Strawberries, and ſuch like fruits, to cool and moiſten.</p>
                  <p>Drink Whey, Sider and ſmall White-wines.</p>
                  <p>Refuſe black wines and ſtale Beer.</p>
                  <p>Keep the body ſoluble, your head will be more free from pain, fumes and heavineſs.</p>
                  <p>Cheriſh ſleep, it refreſheth the ſpirits, paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a troubled minde, and baniſheth cares.</p>
                  <p>Fly idleneſs, the Nurſe of Melancholy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe often and follow buſineſs, or recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:30498:40"/>
                  <p>Walk in the green fields, Orchard, Gardens, Parks, by Rivers and variety of places.</p>
                  <p>Change of Air is very good.</p>
                  <p>Avoid ſolitarineſs, and keep merry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                  <p>Frequent Muſick, ſports and Games.</p>
                  <p>Recreate the ſpirits with ſweet, fragrant and delightful ſmells.</p>
                  <p>Moderate <hi>Venus</hi> good.</p>
                  <p>Baniſh all paſſions as much as in you lies, fear greif, diſpaire, revenge, deſire, jealouſie, emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſuch like,</p>
                  <q>Opus eſt te animo valere ut corpore poſſis.</q>
                  <p>Cicer.</p>
                  <p>Tobacco hurtful (eſpicially if Melancholy be aduſt and a hot body) it heats and exhauſts humidity, makes Melancholly more contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</p>
                  <p>Give not your ſelf to much ſtudy, nor night watchings, they both dry the body, and make humors aduſt, two great enemies to a Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly perſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="precautions">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:30498:40"/>
               <head>Hygiſtic Praecautions and Rules Appropriate to the various diſcraſyes or paſſions of Mind.</head>
               <p>THe Soul and Body are ſo linked and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, as Partners of each others ill and wellfare, that the one is not affected, but the other is drawn into conſent; mutually acting enjoying and ſuffering untill death ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates and breaks the bands of union aſſunder. Hence it is, a diſeaſed body makes a heavy droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping mind; and a wounded, diſturbed or eſtleſs mind, makes a youthful healthy body to decay and languiſh. Who therefore deſires the health and wellfare of the body muſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure eaſe, reſt and tranquility of mind.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Siue Animo Corpus, nec ſine corpore,</l>
                  <l>Animus, bene valere poteſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>SHun Melancholy and ſadneſs as very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deſtructive, occaſioning and producing variety of diſeaſes; ſuffocates and choaks the ſpirits, retards their motion and agility of operation, impriſons, and cloggs them in their Stations, darkens their purity and light debilitating all the faculties
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30498:41"/>of the body, their cheif operator being indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and diſabled; fixeth humors incraſſates and begets obſtructions; and debilitates the Speen, alienates and ſubtracts its ferment from the ſtomack, which decayes both appetite and digeſtion, procures ſcorbute, Hypochondriac Melancholy, pains and tumors of the Spleen, Dropſies. Jaundice, &amp;c. A great Enemy to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſoon changeth florid blooming youth into a pale withering countenance, and makes the whole body to languiſh and decay.</p>
               <p>Mirth ſubtiliates, purifies and chears the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, puts them upon activity that before were torpid dull and heavy, and excites them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and duty in the ſeveral faculties: vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latizeth, rarifies and attenuates groſs feculent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing humors: preſerves youth vigour and beauty; makes the body plump and fat, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panding the ſpirits into the external parts and conveighing nutriment. Whoſe wholſome ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are much the ſame with thoſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, and may well ſupply when that is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>— Dum fata ſinunt</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivite laeti—</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>ANger is the beginning of madneſs which fires the ſpirits, &amp; raiſeth an inteſtine tomult and diſturbance; agitates and inrageth Choler
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30498:41"/>and exaſperates Cholerick diſeaſes: raiſeth hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtericall apoplectic and epileptic fits in thoſe ſubject to them; cauſeth tremblings of the nerves, palpitations of the heart; diſcompoſeth and diſorders the whole body: but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially infirm parts are made ſenſible of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and Cholerick lean bodies.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Maximum remedium irae eſt dilatio.</l>
                  <l>—Dis proximus ille eſt.</l>
                  <l>Quem ratio non ira movet, qui facta rependet</l>
                  <l>Conſilio—</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Claud.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>FEar ſuddenly ſurprizing, enervates and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſpirits to and fro from their reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and faculties ſometimes compreſſing and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to the heart, cauſing violent palpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſuffocation: or ſcattring them from the fountain of life into the external parts, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diſſolution even to exanimation. A long predmeditated and conſtant fear in a remiſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, produceth the ſame effects with Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly.</p>
               <q>Plura ſunt quae nos terrent quam quae Premunt; &amp; ſaepius opinione quam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laboramus.</q>
               <p>LOve &amp; deſire being inordinate and impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſeldom goes alone, but is attended with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30498:42"/>fear, anger, Melancholy, diſpaire, one or more for its conſorts, with which the minde is rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and torn, and variouſly affected as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral paſſions acts their parts by turns: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding difficulties and ſufferings, the ſoul is led away with an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of fervent zeal, deſerts her own manſion, and follows after with an eager proſecution of enjoying, never at home but as a priſoner, and priſoners are but bad houſe keepers: the body needs muſt lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and decay, when the ſoul thus delights and ſtrives to run away.</p>
               <p>For a check to the impetuouſneſs of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate effection and immoderate deſire, take theſe conſiderations to calm, allay, and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late your paſſion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that you cheat your ſelf in ſetting too high a price upon the object of your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and lay out more in expectation, then the income of your deſire obtained can poſſibly make a return: that it is far greater <hi>in non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo,</hi> then it will be <hi>in fruendo;</hi> it will be much leſs when you have, then it ſeems to be now you have it not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the Delirium and fervency of your deſire, does not haſten the accompiſhment of your aymes, but rather retards or fruſtrates: for the extremity and ſtrength of paſſion debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litates and ſuppreſſeth reaſon, the cheif contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and manager of your deſign; puts you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30498:42"/>inconſiderate, immature and raſh attempts, and makes you more unfit, incapable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to effect your purpoſe; for paſſion is alwayes ſpurring, but reaſon hath its ſtops and pauſes, keeps due times for onſets and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that prudent and vigorous action, not innane hungry volition or thirſty deſire though never ſo great, muſt or can acquire the ſatisfaction of your hopes.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that the ardency and heighth of deſire, will not imbetter, ſweeten or add to the heighth of your injoyment when obtained; but rather abate and leſſen it in your account and eſteem: for what thing ſoever you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and are miſtaken and deceived in, you will not vallue at that rate you firſt prized it, but at the worth you now finde it. Vehement &amp; lofty deſires ſcrews you up to ſuch a heighth of expectation, mountain high; but you muſt deſcend into fruition, thats in the valley; and when you find your ſelf in a bottom, and your Sails not ſo filled and puft as formerly by the freſh gailes and blaſts of a ſtrong deſire; your top-ſails then begin to flap and flag when you come into the ſtill calm of fruition, and your lofty ſpirits and high thoughts will lower amain when you Anchor in the Harbour of injoyment: for in appearance it was great when at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſeemingly, but now you are come nearer
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30498:43"/>it is much leſs and inconfiderable really; and what ſwelled you full in the proſecution of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, will not fill you now with ſatisfaction, but prove aery when you graſp it, and ſoon emptied in injoyment.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> it is appointed you muſt or you muſt not obtain the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, which to a rational creature, is ſufficient without other arguments, to qualifie moderate and blunt the keen edge of deſire, and curb the violence of an impetuous affection: but not to cowardiſe, daunt or ſtop a laudible active pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution to attain a noble, vertuous and lawful end, with a moderate ſubmiſſive deſire.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—quiſquis in primo obſtitit</l>
                  <l>Repulitque amorem, tutus ac victor fuit.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>Qui blandiendo dulce nutrivit malum</l>
                  <l>Serò recuſat ferre quod ſubiit jugum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>CAre immoderate and conſtant denies the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal ſpirits their due times for refreſhment, reſt and eaſe; diſables them from duty and the true performance of their Offices, being weary and tired for want of reſpite, heats the ſpirits and dryes the radical moiſture; which changeth a freſh countenance into paleneſs, and pines the body: moſt injurious to thin, lean and Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick bodies.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:30498:43"/>
               <q>Si diis Curae es, quid tua cura poteſt?</q>
               <p>Revenge, jealouſie and envy are the Ulcers of the mind, continually lancinating, corroding or inflaming; introducing a ſecret conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, waſting the ſpirits and radical moiſture, and infeebling all the faculties.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Multis ſe injuriis objicit,</l>
                  <l>—dum una dolet.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>That you may the better know and rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how the paſſions of the mind redound and reflect upon the body to the decay and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of it, and abbreviating life.</p>
               <p>Firſt, conſider that the body without the ſoul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dead and moves not at all: by vertue of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oules conjunction with it, informing and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming it, the body acts with various motions and opperations, and according to the activity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the ſoul, organical aptitude and fitneſs of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody is the exquiſiteneſs and perfection of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perations: the Soul then is agent, the body aſſive, receiving the influx vertue and power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the Soul, who is Rectrix and Gubernatrix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o whom the rule and government belongs: it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> evident therefore ſince the body cannot act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny thing of it ſelf for its conſervation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut the energy and aſſiſtance from the Soul,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30498:44"/>whoſe care is the regulating and moderating the body in all actions external and internal; then the diſtractions, inactivity, wandrings and neglects of the ſoul, does tend to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the due order and government, and conſequently the ruine and diſſolution of the body, which requires a conſtant ſupply of daily reparation and regular tuition for its ſupport and maintenance.</p>
               <p>Now the Soul tranſported by paſſion from its genuine Craſis of placidneſs and tranquility, and reduced into a turbulent, unquiet and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered ſtate, is that condition of incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and unfitneſs for the government for that time being, and many damages ariſe thereby as in each paſſion particularly is enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
               <p>In a threefold manner the Soul is put beſides it ſelf in the regularity of rectory, and is incurious of the welfare of the body.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Soul is either carried away by ſome delightful object, as for ſome thing vehemently deſired, deſerting as it were the body to follow after that thing deſired and coveted, extending her power and ſtrength out of the body, to lay hold, if poſſibly to obtain, and bring within the Sphere and Circle of her enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, the Soul is in fury and diſquiete within, by the apprehenſion of ſome thing aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30498:44"/>and diſturbing it, to which the Soul hath a contrarietie, and antipathy againſt: as in the paſſions of fear, hatred, revenge, anger; and the diſquietude and diſturbance is continued by repreſentations of their Cauſes in the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, which ſtill preſent themſelves to the ſoul, by way of a freſh aſſault, which feeds the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and continues the diſtemper.</p>
               <p>Or thirdly, the Soul is languiſhing, heavy and inactive, altogether indiſpoſed to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and tuition of the body; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps deſirous to be diſcharged and ſhake it off, being weary of the burthen, taking no delight in their partnerſhip and ſociety, as in melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly deſpair and grief.</p>
               <p>In all which caſes you ſhall find the body to ſuffer great prejudice and detriment: But firſt, you muſt conſider how, and by what means or inſtrument, the Soul does act in the body; the Soul acts not immediately, but mediately by the ſpirits, which are the Souls approximate and chief inſtruments in bodily actions and motions, and are appointed their ſeveral Sations, Offices and Duties peculiar to the ſeveral works, as Concoction, Separation, Diſtribution, Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Retention. Aſſimilation, Senſation, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now it will manifeſtly appear how the body is damaged and conſequently the life abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Caſe: when the Soul alienates
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30498:45"/>her ſelf, wanders away with a vehement deſire to procure and obtain any thing moſt agreeable and delightful (at leaſt ſo ſeeming) the Soul as it were contracts it ſelf and unites all her force, ſtands at full bent after this beloved, diſchargeth all her thoughts upon it, and ſpends her ſtrength in deſire and longing; untill at laſt ſhe pines away with a tedious and ſtarving expectation: In the interim the aeconomy and government of her own manſion the body is neglected; the ſpirits, at leaſt a good part are enticed away and called of from their proper and peculiar works and duty, perhaps to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and increaſe the vigour of ſome other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, more immediately ſubſervient and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Souls new deſign and buſineſs; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred far before a good concoction, due excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nutrition, ſeaſonable reſt, or what elſe; and thoſe ſpirits remaining which have the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of theſe duties incumbent on them, have ſo ſmall and inconſiderable ſupport and ſupply of influence from the Soul, to direct and back them in their performance, that the functions are executed ſo weakly and depravedly, to the great prejudice and damage of the body.</p>
               <p>Concoction now is not ſo good, nor the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite ſo quick; the Stomack calls not for a new ſupply, as yet not being well diſcharged and quit of yeſterdayes proviſion: the Stomack now is weary of dreſſing and preparing long
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30498:45"/>Dinners for the body; Lenten and faſting dayes are its vacation from trouble, and beſt contented when leaſt to do.</p>
               <p>Separation now is not ſo good, the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious and nutritious part walk hand in hand together, and paſs without contradiction or due examination: the watch now is not ſo ſtrict at the Ports and privy paſſages, to diſcern what is fit to paſs this way, and what the other, and what to reject and keep out, but promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly receives what preſents it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Diſtribution now is not ſo good, aliment tires by the way, wanting ſpirits to convey and bring it to its journeys end; and exerciſe to jog it on through the anguſt Meanders, and more difficult paſſages.</p>
               <p>Sanguification is now degenerate and vitiate, the preceding requiſites and fit praevious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition being wanting.</p>
               <p>Membrification or aſſimilation is now changed for Cachectic and a depraved habit.</p>
               <p>Excretion and evacuation of what is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and and unfit longer to be retained in the body, is not ſent away in due time, but ſtayes for a paſs, the governeſs is now taken up with other matters, neglects due orders and commands to the expulſive faculty for their emiſſion.</p>
               <p>Neceſſary and wholeſome Cuſtomes are now neglected and diſregarded: the Soul too oft is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30498:46"/>wandring and gadding abroad, and beſt when ſhe is from home; but neglects the airing of her Cottage, and perfuming it with freſh aetherian breath.</p>
               <p>The Soul is now alwayes reſtleſs and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, nor ſhall the ſences her attendants take their due repoſe, but keeps an unqiet houſe at midnight.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Caſe: the regular and due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of government in the body is ſubverted and changed, when the Soul in the forementioned paſſions, of fear, anger, hatred or revenge, is diſturbed and a arum'd by the aſſault, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or appearance of ſome evill or injury; the Soul then ſummons the ſpirits together from thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> common duties, and calls them to her aid and aſſiſtance, for ſecurity from danger, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe the violence offered or revenge the injury; hurrying them here and there, from one part to another in a tumultuous manner, if the aſſault be ſuddain and ſurprizing; ſometimes inward to ſupport the heart, to give courage and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which by their ſuddain concourſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to the Center; cauſeth great palpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſometimes ſuffocation: or elſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to the out-works, into the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts, to repell the invaſion and violence of the evil preſenting or approaching, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the quarrel: the hands and arms then receive a double or trebble ſtrength, the Muſcles
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30498:46"/>being full and diſtended with agile ſpirits for their activity and ſtrength in motion: the eyes then are ſtaring full and ſtretcht fourth with a croude of inflamed ſpirits, darting fourth their fury and ſpending their ſtrength upon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary and object of their trouble: the tongue then is ſwelled with ſpirits and bigg words, that wanting a larger room for vent, tumbles out broken and imperfect ſpeeches, and ſcarce can utter whole words: The Leggs and Feet then have an Auxiliary ſupply, and double portion of ſpirits conveighed in to their ſinews, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their agility and ſtrength, to come on or off: but in the mean time the heart perhaps is almoſt fainting, ſo long being deprived off, and deſerted by, thoſe lively vigorous ſpirits, which did inhabit and quarter there for its Life-guard, protection and ſupport; are now called off their Guard and common duties, imployed in Forreign parts, commanded here and there as the emergent occaſion preſents it ſelf to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs of this Microcoſme.</p>
               <p>In the third Caſe mentioned: the due order, government, and neceſſary execution of offices and duties belonging to the welfare and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the body and preſervation of life, is neglected and weakly performed.</p>
               <p>When the ſoul being darkned and overſpread with a cloud of ſadneſs, betakes her ſelf to a ſullen incurious recumbency and retiredneſs wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30498:47"/>to reſign and caſt off the government and tuition of the body; and as a burthen which ſhe delights not now to bear about, begins to looſe her hold, who before had embraced and clipt ſo cloſe; ſuſpending the vertue of her energy and vigorous emanations; but now acting faintly and coldly, thoſe neceſſary mutual performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without regard to their former friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or their future conjunct preſervation. The body now begins to ſinck with its own weight, and preſs towards the Earth the natural place from whence it came. That aetherian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which before had boyed it up and took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſport it to and fro, is now ready to let it fall and groueſ downwards, to leave it whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it muſt goe. The wonted pleaſures of their partnerſhip and ſociety, is now diſguſted and rejected: food now hath loſt its reliſh and is become unſavory: ſleep which before was pleaſant as a holy day in the fruition of reſt and eaſe, is now compoſed of nothing but troubleſome unquier dreams, linked together with ſome fighing intervals, to meaſure out the weary night by. Exerciſe and ſporting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ereations is now accounted druggery and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious toyling: unwilling is the ſoul to move her yokfellow, farther then the enforcing law of nature and neceſſity commands and urgeth. their joynt operations which before were duly and unanimouſly performed, are now ceaſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30498:47"/>or depraved, by the retraction, relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctance and indiſpoſed ſadneſs of the ſoul to act: the wonted vigorous emanations of the ſoul, and her radiant influence upon the ſpirits is now ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, ſubducted and called back. Theſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring attending ſpirits and cheifeſt agents, which at a beck were alwaies ready agile and active in the execution of her commands now want commands to ſtir and warrants to act by: but in a torpid and ſomnolent diſpoſition, unfit for action and the exquiſite performance of their duties, and in a ſympathizing compliance with the ſoul the excitrix and rectrix of their motions, are ready to reſign their offices, and give over working, that what they now do is faintly and remiſſely performed, with much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency &amp; depravation. When the ſoul is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and merry, the ſpirits dance and are cheirfull at their work; but when ſhe droops and mourns, the ſpirits are dull, heavy and tired, the functions weakly and inſufficiently executed.</p>
               <p>From the preceeding diſcourſe may eaſily be collected, that the diſtempers and alienations of the ſoul from her genuine craſis of ſerenity and quietude, is of great diſadvantage, to health; impreſſing upon the body various preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral effects, forming the Ideas and charracters of diſeaſes upon the ſpirits, and by them commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, conveighed and propagated in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: likewiſe the morbific ſeeds &amp; ſecret chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30498:48"/>of diſeaſes which lay dead and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active, are by the aeconomical diſturbance and perturbations of minde, awakened, moved and ſtirred up to hoſtility and action which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would have layen dormant; as by greif, fear or anger; hyſterical paſſions, ſwoonings, epilepſies, &amp;c. Are often procured; and it is evident, and commonly obſerved by infirme and diſeaſed people, how paſſion agravates and heighthens their diſtempers; and acccording to the temper of their mindes will their bodily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities be agravated or abated.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this ſubject with three corollaryes being the Epitome of what hath been aſſerted and aimed at.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no perturbation or paſſion of mind, whether little or great, but it works a real effect in the body more or leſs, according to the nature and ſtrength of the paſſion; and by how much the more ſuddain, great, often, and longer duration the paſſion is by ſo much are the impreſſions and effects worſe, more dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and indeleable. You cannot be angry or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious or Melancholly, or give way to any ſuch paſſion, but you cheriſh and feeed an enemy that preys upon your life, and you may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that paſſion makes as great nay greater alteration within the body; then the change of your countenance appears to outward view, which is not a little, although but the ſhadow
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30498:48"/>or reflections of the inward diſtemper and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order: and were it poſſible by any perſpective to ſee the alteration and diſcompoſure within made by a paſſionate minde, the proſpect would be ſtrange, and much different from that pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidneſs and tranquility of an indiſturbed quiet ſoul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Strong and vehement paſſions or affections of the mind to intent upon this or that object, whether deſiderable, or formidable and to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, alienates ſuſpends &amp; draws of the wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vigour influence and preſervative power of the ſoul due to the body; whereby the functions and operations are not duly and ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but intempeſtively remiſſly and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: nor is the dammage onely privative, but alſo introduceth and impreſſeth upon the ſpirits a morbific idea, which is <hi>ens reale &amp; ſeminale,</hi> producing this or that effect, according to the nature and property of the Idea received, and aptitude of the recipient ſubject. Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Idea's are let in naked, but they ſtrait are inveſted and cloathed in the body, have a real exiſtence, and are <hi>entia realia;</hi> though at firſt conception but <hi>entia rationis:</hi> as the longing of a pregnant woman, being but the Idea of a thing in her minde, begets various and real diſtempers in her body, if not ſoon ſatisfyed; and ſometimes charactrized up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Embryo in the Wombe. Likewiſe a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30498:49"/>good ſtomack is taken off its meat ſuddenly, by the comming of ſome unwelcome bad news; the appetite is gone now the ſoul is diſquieted, and the Body really affected and altered: let this ſad tidings be contradicted, and the Soul ſatisfied of the truth to the contrary, it ſets a new impreſſion upon the ſpirits, they ſtrait are cheered, lively and active; the ſtomack calls for meat and drink, and the faculties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their wonted operations. Whereby it appears, the two paſſions of joy and grief, as they are oppoſite in their objects, ſo are their effects wrought in the body, as far diſtant and different.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A cogitative or contemplative perſon to intent, alwayes or unſeaſonably employing the mind ſeriouſly and eagerly either in real or ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matters, fabricating Idea's upon the ſpirits, diſturbs and hinders other neceſſary offices and opperations conſervative of being, enervates and weakens their performance in duty, impares health, and haſtens old age: but thoſe that live moſt incurious, and void of ſtudious thoughts and ſerious cogitations, preſerve the ſtrength of nature and integrity of all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, protract the verduce and beauty of youth, much longer from declenſions and decay; for by how much the rational faculty is over buſie and imtempeſtively exerciſed, drawing the full vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the ſoul into the exerciſe of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30498:49"/>and robbing other inferiour functions of their neceſſary influential ſupply, and emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power from the ſoul; by ſo much the other faculties are impoveriſhed and abated, their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions more languid and depraved: and therefore it is, a cloſe Students life, diſpoſeth and inclines to many infirmities, enervates and debilitates nature, abbreviates and ſhortens its courſe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fieri non potest, ut animo malè affecto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non etiam unà laboret corpus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>parcè bibe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>frugaliter ede</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>utere exercitio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>rarò venere</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>diluculo ſurge</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>tranquillo ſis animo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>tempeſtivè fac omnia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>immodice nihil.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ars brevis, vitam trahit longam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:30498:50"/>
               <head>Of Fontanels or iſſues.</head>
               <p>NAture having appointed the Body to be preſerved and nouriſhed by a continual ſupply of neceſſary food daily to be received in, which before it be aſſimilated and incorporated into the ſubſtance of the body, ſuffers ſeveral concoctions and tranſmutations by the digeſtive ferment of the parts, deſtinated for that office and work: in which praevious diſpoſition and gradual preparation for nutrition there is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration made, the nutritive and neceſſary part from the excrementitious and unneceſſary; the pureſt defaecated part ordained for aliment, is conveyed ſtill farther from one digeſtion to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, untill it hath received the compliment and full perfection intended by nature: the excrementitious and inutile part ſegregated, is received by ſinks and channels peculiarly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and framed for their conveyance out of the Body as the lower guts, Urinary ductures, Noſe, Pores, &amp;c. Which paſſages if at any time obſtructed and ſtopt up, the derriment and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible dammage ſoon confirms the neceſſity of their uſe &amp; office. And as nature hath appointed and framed in the Body vents and out-lets for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30498:50"/>the daily diſcharging of excrementious ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, which otherwiſe would putrifie, ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and ſtifle, if not in ſome meaſure duly eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated.</p>
               <p>In imitation of natures contrivance, Art hath invented Iſſues as Ports and Vents to be placed here or there, as the variety of occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions require, to ſupply natures inſufficiency and inability to relieve and help her ſelf in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge and emiſſion of ſuperfluous extravaſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed humours and putrid vapours; which retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, produce various ſymptomes, according to the ſeveral proprieties of their nature, and degeneration, organicall difference, and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier office of the parts they invade and infeſt.</p>
               <p>And having ſuch a paſſe Port, by which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture findes her ſelf alleviated and diſburthened, does daily amandate and ſend ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to this out let, as to other common paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and conveyances for the excretion and voiding of excrements, by her own inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fabrication.</p>
               <p>And having found ſuch an auxiliary conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency, ſhe does expect it to be continued, and relies upon the aſſiſtance, untill the occaſion be otherwiſe prevented, the cauſe removed, or nature better able to diſcharge and free her ſelf, by the channels and paſſages of her own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
               <p>Now if praematurely and unſeaſonably, this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30498:51"/>artificial paſſage be denyed and ſtopt up, there being cauſe for the contrary; the confluence of humours meeting and gathering at the place, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurgitates back again with a united force and greater current, at which nature being ſurpriſed unexpectedly, and having made no proviſion to ſecure her ſelf from ſuch a retrogradation or reflux, produceth the ſame preternatural ſymptoms and effects, for which the iſſue was firſt made or worſe.</p>
               <p>For your better ſatisfaction and information in the uſe of iſſues: firſt I ſhall conſider for whom and in what caſes beneficial; Secondly, what it is that iſſues forth and is evacuated; Thirdly, the places and parts of the body pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and conveniant for them; Laſtly, the ſignes when to cloſe them without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>For corpulent and plethorick bodyes, that feed high and live a ſedentary inactive life, whereby ventilation and tranſpiration is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and reſtrained, iſſues may be uſed by way of Praecaution.</p>
               <p>In Cachectic bodies and diſeaſes from putrid humours; iſſues makes evacuation and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates.</p>
               <p>For revulſion, derivation or interception of a humour inconveniently reſorting to an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, or infirm part, iſſues alters the courſe and current.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:30498:51"/>
               <p>In Diſeaſes from venenate and noxious va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, appearing with uncertaine motions, and intervals; iſſues retards, and abates the ſtrength of their paroxyſmes.</p>
               <p>For Eiratic pains <hi>Cutany defaedations</hi> and extu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berations from extravaſated humors, &amp; fruſtrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous digeſtion; the uſe of iſſues may be beneficial.</p>
               <p>Iſſues are as Rivulets or Channels from a fountain to prevent inundation, and direct the ſtreams: they do not deſtroy the Spring, but give vent and current this way, that it ſhall not overflow to do hurt otherwaies. They do not eradicate a diſeaſe, but they leſſen and abate the ſwelling productions or growth, prevent or retard the frequent paroxyſmes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of formidable and dolorous ſymptoms; give time and ſpace for a Phyſician to uſe fit efficacious Medicines to extirpate, and take away the antecedent cauſe; and are but <hi>remedia a poſteriori, &amp; palliativa,</hi> to mitigate the effects, not curative and eradicative.</p>
               <p>For the nature and quality of humors iſſuing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they are divers, according to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpoſition of bodyes, temperaments and morbific cauſes; ſuch as the body abounds with and is ſuperfluanous, ſuch is tranſmitted thither for emiſſion.</p>
               <p>That the humour evacuated is not uſefull and neceſſary for the body: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears firſt by the concomitant figns mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30498:52"/>the nature of it: itching, pricking ſharp pain about the place, inflamation and ſpongious fleſh riſing, in ſome more, in others leſs; which are not ſigns and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a natural good humor, but a hot corroding, ſharp, unnatural humor flowing thither, degenerate and corrupt: beſide, nature is not prodigal in the excretion and expence of humors, profitable and uſeful for the body, except by irritation.</p>
               <p>What is the reaſon that in cachectic foul bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes Ulcers in any part are difficult to cure? but by reaſon of a continual ſupply of bad humors, reſorting thither for eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation, and will not let the ſore heale up becauſe they will have vent: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a skilful Chirurgeon, does not only apply topical Medicaments, but alſo endeavours to remove the antecedent cauſe, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal medicine and reduce the Cacochymical ill habit of body to a natural good ſtate and condition by alteration and evacuatioy which being procured, the wonted flu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> humors to the ulcerated place is ſtaied, and then nature heals the ſore with a very little help.</p>
               <p>In placing of Iſsues rightly, three things is to be conſidered; Firſt that they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious and properly ſcituate for the afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and effiux of the morbific humor; for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30498:52"/>humors have a tendency and an inclination to one part more then to another, according to the communication of parts, and rather down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards then upwards, from the propenſity of their gravity: Secondly, whether Revulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or derivation of the morbific cauſe be moſt convenient and benificial, in the caſe for which an iſſue is appointed. Thirdly, That the poſition and motion of the Muſcles be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerved, elſe the Iſſue will not be ſo beneficial nor lye eaſy; for if it be ſet upon a Muſcle the motion and attrition of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcle will continually moleſt and diſturb it, and the evacuation will be but little: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt endeavour to place them in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſtitiis Muſculorum,</hi> in the diſtances between the Muſcles where the extravaſated humors are moſt frequent in their motions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulations.</p>
               <p>In the Cloſing up of an iſſue theſe are to be conſidered: the cauſe for which it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, what effects alteration or abatement of infirmity; the age of the perſon, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in youth, ſtrength of nature, or decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning years; as alſo the ſeaſon and time of the year: which is to be adjudged and determined variouſly, as the particular caſe and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances collated do ſuggeſt; but generally the body is to be accounted in a better or worſe ſtate and condition, as the humor iſsuing is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30498:53"/>better or worſe; thin, ſharp, bloody or fowle, ſmelling ſtrong or ſtincking, much in quantity; declare the body to be cacochymical and foul, the humors depraved and degenerate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the iſsue to be continued: but the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iſsuing white, reſonable thick, ſweet, little in quantity, and not ſharp cauſing pain, nor inflamation about the place, are good ſignes and ſhew ſoundneſs of body, the humors to be in their natural condition, amicable and friendly to the body, and permit an Iſsue to be cloſed up: but let due purgation immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſucceed, and a ſpare dyet.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:30498:53"/>
            <head>BELLUM NECESSARIUM. <hi>SIVE</hi> MEDICUS BELLIGERANS; The Military or Practical Phyſician re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing his <hi>ARMORY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Furniſhed with Medicinal Armature and Weapons, offenſive and defenſive, Anatomically fitted and appropriate</p>
            <list>
               <item>To the Head
<list>
                     <item>Capital Pills.</item>
                     <item>Cephalic eſſence.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Lungs
<list>
                     <item>Pectoral Electuary.</item>
                     <item>Balſamic Extract.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:30498:54"/>
               <item>Heart
<list>
                     <item>Cordial Tincture.</item>
                     <item>Bezoardic Confection.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack
<list>
                     <item>Stomack Pills.</item>
                     <item>Digeſtive Elixir.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Spleen Meſentery and Liver
<list>
                     <item>Cachectic Fills.</item>
                     <item>Scorbute Tincture.</item>
                     <item>Hydropic Pills.</item>
                     <item>Hydropic Powder.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Guts
<list>
                     <item>Aperitive Powder.</item>
                     <item>Retentive Powdex.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Reins and Bladder
<list>
                     <item>Nephritic Extract.</item>
                     <item>Nephritic Powder.</item>
                     <item>Dyſuretic Powder.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:30498:54"/>
               <item>Genital Parts
<list>
                     <item>Reſtaurative Eſſence.</item>
                     <item>Hyſterical Pills.</item>
                     <item>Expulſive Powder.</item>
                     <item>Reſtringent powder.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Joynts
<list>
                     <item>Arthritic Pills.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Skin
<list>
                     <item>Coſmetic Water.</item>
                     <item>Powder of Saturn.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Miſcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laneous
<list>
                     <item>Italick Pills</item>
                     <item>Neapolitan Pills.</item>
                     <item>Haematic Powder.</item>
                     <item>Febrific Elixir.</item>
                     <item>Sarcotic Pills.</item>
                     <item>Sudorific Pills.</item>
                     <item>Sympathetic powder.</item>
                     <item>Iſſue Cerecloth.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:30498:55"/>
            <head>The Vertues uſe and Doſes of each Medicine.</head>
            <div type="medicines">
               <head>For the Head.</head>
               <p>THE Capital Pills are appointed for infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the brain and nerves, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuates noxious humours that moleſt and hinder the exerciſe of the rational faculty; or obſtruct and impedite the free operation of the ſenſitive; whereby the animal ſpirits are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviated, the ventricles of the brain and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans for ſence freed from obſtructions; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing much to the cure of infirmities afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head and nerves as lethargies, apoplexy and ſoporiferous diſeaſes; Convulſions epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, palſies, vertigoes, tremors; pains of the head, rhumes, dul ſight, or hearing,</p>
               <p>Take them after your firſt ſleep; or halfe the doſe when you go to bed, the reſt at 5 or 6 of the clock next morning; in ſo doing you will not be called up before your due time to riſe. When you are up, drink ſome warm poſſet-drink,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30498:55"/>and walk about the houſe: Eat at noon; thus do 3 or 4 dayes together for they operate gently.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for men and women is 5 or 6 Pills: for 14 years old, 4 Pills.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cephalic eſſence,</hi> is ſpecifickly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to the head, effectually reſiſting the infirmities thereof, and ſtrengthening the brain and nerves of ſpecial uſe for ſuch as are catalep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, epileptick, apoplectick, paralytick; that have a cold or moiſt bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, ſunject to rhumes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, remblings or weakneſs of the nerves, vertigoes, paines of the head: it ſtrengthens a weak memory, weak eyes, amends dull hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if the defect be not organicall. It quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens and raiſeth the ſpirits in ſomnolent drowzy perſons, makes them more acute and vigilant, and roborates the animal faculty.</p>
               <p>To be taken after the Capitall Pills, if both be uſed.</p>
               <p>Take it in the morning faſting, thus: Drop it upon fine powdered ſugar, and take it upon a knifes point; then drink a draught of what liquor is moſt agreeable and proper for you: eat an hour after and go abroad. Alſo you may apply it to the noſe profitably; Whereby the vertue is received into the head.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for men and women is 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drops, for children and infants ſo many drops as they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30498:56"/>are years old. If under a year old, only apply it to the noſe, as aforeſaid, and alſo to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Shake the bottle when you uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <head>For the Lungs</head>
               <p>THe infirmities moſt incident to the Lungs are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A thin ſharp rheum, irritating and provoking the Lungs to expulſion by coughing which oftentimes procures an exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceration and ſpitting of bloud, and from hence a Conſumption may inſue.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. A groſſe indigeſted flegm, ſtopping the veſſels of the Lungs and pipes for reſpiration, cauſing difficulty of breathing, wheezing and coughing, which is called an Aſthma.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. A Conſumption or Ulcer of the Lungs, which in the beginning not ſo eaſy to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but to be known by theſe ſigns. An ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſe or heavy pain in the breaſt, ſhort breath, frequent coughing, and deſtillation upon the Lungs. In time is made more manifeſt, by ſpitting of purulent matter, an ulcerous and more ſharp pain in the breaſt, a putrid Feaver, the cough more vehement, imbecillity and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all the faculties, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the infirmities aforeſaid the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30498:56"/>following are effectual and peculiarly appointed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pectoral electuary,</hi> ſtayes defluctions of ſharp thin rheums that invade the Lungs, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigates their acidity and ſaltneſs which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers Corroſion, ſpitting of bloud, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; checks the violence of coughing and eaſeth the breaſt: it helps a dry cough, looſens flegm, and helps expectoration, procures reſt, and reſpite from coughing in the night.</p>
               <p>To be taken at any time, the quantity of a nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg or more, but chiefly at night and morning in bed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Balſamic extract,</hi> is moſt effectual in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring weak, decayed Conſumptive or ulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lungs; purifies and clenſeth the breaſt from putrid matter that cauſeth the breath to ſtink or be ill ſavoured; defends the Lungs from te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid maligne vapours, internally generated or externally received, inducing a vitious depraved conſtitution of the Lungs, or promoting a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; roborates and ſtrengthens the Lungs, firmly reſiſting an haereditary Phthiſical conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive diſpoſition ſubject to ſome families: Opens obſtructions &amp; ſtoppings in the breaſt, from Crude viſcous phlegm ſtuffing the pipes of the Lungs and veſſels for reſpiration; helps old coughs aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hmatic wheezings, difficult, ſhort, and faint breathing, from indiſpoſition decay or imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillity
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30498:57"/>of the vital parts, and reſtores their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and natural ability.</p>
               <p>Attenuates, maturates and concocts tough raw flegm, and facilitates expectoration; retracts a confluence of crude humors flowing in upon the Lungs by the <hi>arteria venoſa,</hi> cauſing oppila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, ſhort breath and Pertinacious coughing. Is both a preſervative and curative medicine for perſons Conſumptive, inclining or diſpoſed thereto, by any Pectoral infirmity.</p>
               <p>The Doſe is half a dram for Man or Woman. For 14 years old, a ſcruple or 24 grains.</p>
               <p>Take it night and morning in bed: if it be for putrid or ulcerated Lungs you muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the uſe of it 3 weeks or a month obſerving due order and dyet: if for leſſer infirmities a ſhorter time will effect the intention. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines you not to the houſe, more then the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of your own body, and the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of weather prohibits you to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
               <p>Rowl it in Sugar-Candy, or fine powdered ſugar, and take it upon a knifes point and ſwallow it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:30498:57"/>
               <head>For the Heart.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Cordial Tincture,</hi> is appointed for fainting fits, it cheers the heart, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leives the vital ſpirits opreſſed, cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth decayed nature in weak and antient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; comforts and warmes a cold ſtomack, helps digeſtion, expells winde and Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly vapours from the Spleen; very good for palpitations of the heart, or oppreſſion at the ſtomack through Crudities and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted matter.</p>
               <p>To be taken at any time night or day, when any the aforeſaid occaſions require.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is a ſpoonful; for twelve years old, half a ſpoonfull, and ſo proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably to younger.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bezoardic Confection,</hi> is a Soveraign Antidote againſt the Plague and all contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Feavers; it powerfully expells poyſons, breaths out all putrid matter and malignity, received by unwholſome Airs, or otherwiſe generated in the body: effectuall in the Small-Pox, Meaſels, Spotted-feavers to bring forth their Malignity to the skinn, and to prevent returning inwards: removes oppreſſions at the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30498:58"/>heart, and any ſurfeit or over-charging of the ſtomack, by intemperate eating or drinking; of excellent uſe in all ſuddaine Sickneſſes in young or old, to defend the heart and vitalls, until the diſtemper manifeſt it ſelf: Neceſſary to carry with you in Travel.</p>
               <p>Take it on a knifs point, or diſſolve it in Poſſet-drink, as oft as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is the quantity of a Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut, for fourteen years old, as much as a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg; for ſeven years old, the bigneſs of a Haſel-nut. And ſo proportionably to youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <head>For the Stomack.</head>
               <p>THe Stomack not performing its office rightly in Chylification, either by its own weakneſs or otherwiſe impedited, layes the foundation of many diſeaſes, and therefore is primely to be fortyfied and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when any dificiency appears: for, error in the firſt concoction is not amended in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing digeſtions of other parts from whence various preternatural affects diſſeminated in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30498:58"/>divers parts of the body owning their riſe and ſpring from this fountain.</p>
               <p>The ſymptoms of an ill affected ſtomack are, fulneſs, heavineſs or opreſſion, loſs of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, ſlow digeſtion or depraved, nauſeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or vomitting, hicket or belching, thirſt, heat, or burning. For which the following Medicines are appointed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Stomack Pills</hi> cleanſeth the firſt region of the body downwards, from abounding Choller and Phlegm, evacuates and unloads an opreſſed ſtomack, from humors and indigeſted matter that corrupts good nutriment, dulls the appetite and hinders digeſtion; by their abſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive faculty, removes viſcous Phlegm impacted in the tunicles of the ſtomack, a receptacle for inflation and wind. Prevents, diarrhaeas, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enterial and dyſenterial Fluxes, gripings and pains in the ſtomack and bowels, from ſharp biting Choller or flatulent crudity by taking away their cauſes. And leaving a greateful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction upon the ſtomack which promotes concoction. Deſtroyes Worms, and prevents, their breeding by carrying away putrid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof they are generated.</p>
               <p>Takes away bitter eructations and nauſeous belchings, vellications and gripes in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack from bilious acrid humors; makes the ſtomack clean and fit for the reception of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:30498:59"/>wholſome food, and then you may expect good nutriment.</p>
               <p>Take them after your firſt ſleep, or eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning: when you are up, Drink ſome warme Poſſet, eat at noon. You may go abroad if the weather be warm, and the condition of your body will ſafely permit; But otherwiſe keep houſe.</p>
               <p>You may take them three or four dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they work gently.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Men and Women is five or ſix Pills; For the age fourteen, 4 Pills.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Digeſtive Elixir,</hi> By its inciſive and attenuating quality is very auxiliary to the ſtomacks ferment deficient and decayed, or obtunded and overlayed with crudityes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the imbecillity and indiſpoſition of the ſuperior orifice of the ſtomack, and cauſeth the ſtomack to cloſe with more delight and ſatisfaction upon its object. Prevents nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, flarulent belchings, nidorous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavory riſings in the ſtomack from indigeſtion and putrid fermentation. Kills Worms in the ſtomack and Guts; And amends a ſtrong offenſive breath. By its ſaline quality, excites and quickens a dull appetite and procures good digeſtion. By its Balſamic amaritude, is heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and grateful to a watriſh, crude raw ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:30498:59"/>
               <p>By its aromatic vertue, cheriſheth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth a weak tender ſtomack.</p>
               <p>But if the ſtomack be very foul, ſtuffed and clogged with groſs Phlegmatick humors, then firſt clenſe downward with the ſtomack Pills, or upwards by vomit, if hot Cholerick aduſt humors fluctuate, heate and broyl up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtomack: afterward ſtrengthen with the uſe of this <hi>Elixir,</hi> and you will finde a great alteration both for appetite and digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſtomack much alleviated, diſburthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cheerful in the performance of its office.</p>
               <p>Drop it in a little fine powdred Sugar, and take it upon a knives point, in the morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; you may drink after it Wine, Beer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Liquor moſt agreeable to your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack: eat an hour after and go abroad: you may take it likewiſe at four of Clock in the afternoon.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for men and Women is ſixteen drops: for the age fourteen ten drops; for eight years old ſix drops: and ſo proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably to younger.</p>
               <p>Continue the uſe of it a fortnight together. Shake the bottle when you uſe it,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:30498:60"/>
               <head>Medicines appropriate to the Spleen, Meſentery and Liver.</head>
               <p>THe Cachectic Pills are effectuall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the defects and infirmities of the Spleen, meſentery Liver and Gall, from whence ariſe a Cachectic or ill habit of body, Dropſies, Scurvy, <hi>Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driac</hi> Melancholy, Jaundice black and yellow, obſtructions and pains in the ſeveral parts na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, various praeternatural febrific aeſtuations and fermentations, crudityes and coagulations in thoſe parts primarily affected, from thence deſſuſed and diſperced into the maſs of blood, which being thereby vitiated and impure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth various external Symptomes, pallid and livid diſcolourations, ſcorbute ſpots and deſaedations of the skin, Tumors and Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
               <p>Theſe Pills evacuate and clenſe gently, by which the fore named parts are exonerated, and notably reſtored to their priſtine vigour and due performance of their office (but by ſtrong purgatives debilitated.) They penetrate into the ſecond and third digeſtion, removing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and attenuating viſcous coagulations which obtund the ſpirits in their motion and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30498:60"/>activity, ſtop the conveyance of nutriment and corrupting it, hindering the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of parts, neceſſarily ſubordinate and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient one to the other in their offices and duties, and retaining excrements of the ſeveral digeſtions which ought duly to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated and ſent forth, from whence the ill effects that enſue are numerous. They are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent in prevention, and compoſing unnatural fermentations and turgid ebullitions in the bloud and humors; from whence Erratic pains, and various diſquietudes. They imbibe and drink up (by their alkalizate quality) ſharp and acide humors which cauſe eroſions and torſions of the bowells, ſtimulating and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Fluxes, and ſharp pricking pains in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts.</p>
               <p>They depurate and renovate the bloud from ſcorbutic degeneration and exotic mixture by which the ſpirits recover ſtrength and vigour which before were alienated torpid and inactive, the organs for nutrition disburthened and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived and made fit to performe and execute their ſeveral offices and functions.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Men and Women, is 4 or 5 Pills: (According to the ſtrength, and condion of their body to operate.) For the age 14, 3 Pills.</p>
               <p>Take them early in the morning, you may ſleep 2 hours after; when you are up drink a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30498:61"/>draught of poſſet drink; eat at noon:</p>
               <p>Thus do twice or thrice in the weak, continuing their uſe more or leſs, as the occaſſion and greatneſs of the cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
               <p>After theſe Pills the following <hi>Tincture</hi> is very proper and beneficial.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Scorbute Tincture</hi> hath a ſpecific vertue againſt the Scurvy, which diſcovers it ſelf by certain ſymptomes attending it, as laſſitude, heavineſs and indiſpoſition to motion or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; pains of the head, thighs, hips, knees, and other parts; putrefaction of the gums and looſneſs of teeth, inflation and diſtention of the <hi>Hypochonders;</hi> red purple or livid ſpots upon the skin, &amp;c. Some of theſe ſigns are ſufficient to declare the diſeaſe eſpecially when remote cauſes concur, as a cloſe Air, groſs diet, ſtudious, melancholy or ſedentary life. This <hi>Tincture</hi> aſiſts the ſpleen in the diſcharge of its office, from whoſe imbecillity and depraved operation chiefly, as an approximate cauſe, the bloud acquires a peculiar corruption and ſcorbutic malignity, detected by ſome ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes declaring its ſpecific nature, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the degree or heigth arrived at, are the ſymptomes more in number, and more exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate &amp; worſe in quality. The <hi>Tincture</hi> reſolveth
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30498:61"/>and volatizeth coagulate and fixed tartareous matter; attenuates and rarenes groſs ſubſiding humours, which obſtruct the veſsels of the Spleen and viſcera of nutrition, cauſing turgid inflations, ſchirrous tumors and pains in thoſe parts, concocts crude ichorous bloud, depurates and renovates it from ſcorbutick feculency, and maligne putrefaction, makes it more fit for nutrition, and amicable to the body.</p>
               <p>Take it in a glaſs of White-wine, or Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh which is beſt; or in good ſtrong beer, not new; or beer with the juce of Orange which is better; or whey if the body be hot. In the morning faſting, and at 4 of the clock in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noon.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for men and women is 24 drops: for the age 14 and under, ſo many drops as they are years old.</p>
               <p>Shake the Bottle then uſe it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hydropic Pills</hi> are appointed for the cure of Dropſies, and watery tumors of the body, whether univerſal or in particular parts: They are purgative, and attract ſerous and watery humors from any part of the body and Evacuates by ſeige. They excite the kidneys to attraction and expulſion, which before was fluggiſh, imbecile or impedited in their office, whereby ſuperfluous ſeroſity or water is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated and retained in the body; they are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30498:62"/>very aperitive reſolutive and diuretical, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſtructions of the Liver, Spleen and Ure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, diſſolving any coagulate matter and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the Morbific cauſe by Urine.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Men and Women is 5 Pills; or but 4 if a tender body; for 14 years old, 3 Pills.</p>
               <p>Take them in the morning faſting, and drink little until noon; then eat your dinner. Thus doe 2 or 3 days in a week intermitting a day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween. Thoſe dayes you purge not, drink a draught of Wormwood wine, and eat ſome white bisket every morning, and at 4 of the Clock after noon: keep a ſpare diet, let your meat be roſted rather then boyled. If your ſtomack be weak uſe the digeſtive <hi>Tincture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be moderate in drinking. You may profitably uſe white-wine mingled with the decoction of ſaſaffras, two parts to one of wine.</p>
               <p>The Hydropic powder hath the ſame ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and operation with the Hydropic Pills. But becauſe ſome are averſe to Pills, that with facility can take a powder, they may chuſe either.</p>
               <p>Take it in a draught of poſſet drink or white wine warmed. Obſerving the preceding direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is one Dram: for the age 14, 2 ſcruples or half a Dram. And ſo proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to younger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:30498:62"/>
               <head>For the Guts.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Retentive Powder,</hi> mittigates and ſtayes all Fluxes and violent excretions of the Guts, whether lienterial Dyſenterial or diarrhaea's; not by an aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent or binding quality of the Medicine, that were injurious to nature and not ſubſidiary, to retaine what nature deſires to expel; but by attracting and collecting the peccant humor that ſtimulates to expulſion and evacuating it, whereby one ſtoole that the Medicine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, carryes with it more of the offending cauſe, then ſix other from the (oft times vain) irritations and ſtruglings of nature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>By the anodynous vertue, it allayes &amp; charms the turgid aeſtuation of ſtimulating humors, by degrees evacuates and ſends them forth, with leſs diſturbance and danger; whether they be ſharp, bilious, or acide ſerous humors; a ſaline irritating Phleme, a ſtinking corrupt Colliquation, or acrid and aduſt Melancholy; having alſo and aſtringent vertue to bind after wards, and to roborate the retentve faculty, the offending cauſe being removed; this is the ſafeſt way to ſtop the flux of what nature ſoever, and in any perſon; women with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30498:63"/>child, in child bed, children or infants, and to prevent the danger that may enſue. If the Flux be bloody drink Whey wherein gads of Steel hath been quenched, for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon drink.</p>
               <p>The Doſe of the Powder for man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is a dram or more: to a Child of twelve years old, half a dram. And ſo proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to younger.</p>
               <p>Take it in Poſſet-drink, in the Morning in bed, and ſleep after it if you can. Do likewiſe the next day, if the occaſion continue.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Apperitive powder,</hi> is emollient ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterfive and opening, appointed for coſtive, hot and dry bodys; whereby excrements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too long retained, are hardned and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſumes return up to the ſtomack, troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Concoction and offenſive to the brain: it corrects the dry diſtemper of the Guts, or intemperate heat of the Liver (frequent cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of coſtiveneſs) humects and ſoftens dry hard excrements, and procures two or three ſtools. It is a neceſſary preparative to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, making the body f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uid and fit for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; opening obſtructions of the bowels, meſentery, Liver, Spleen Pancreas and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix; whereby any Medicine hath acceſs to thoſe parts, with more facility and ſpeed and leſs abatement of its ſtrength, before it comes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:30498:63"/>to operate upon the part intended; the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and paſſages being laid open, by its Apperitive vertue.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is a Dram: for fourteen years, two ſcruples.</p>
               <p>Take it in a wine-glaſs full of the Liquor of ſtewed Prunes, in the morning faſting; half an hour after drink a good draught of poſſet drink, or Whey if you have a hot coſtive body: an hour after this you may eat your breakfaſt; ſpoon meat is beſt.</p>
               <p>Thus you may do four or five mornings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <head>For the Reins and Bladder.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Nephritic Extract,</hi> by a ſpecific vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue reſiſts the lapidifactory diſpoſition of the Reins, and petrifactive ſuccus, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents coagulation and petrifaction: By the abſterſive tartareous property, clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Reins and Bladder from muci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laginous ſlimy matter, ſand or gravel that lodgeth in the urinary paſſages. By the unctuous quality, mollifies, relaxeth lubrifies and dilates the uriters and urinary ductures,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:30498:64"/>for the more facile and ſpeedy excluſion of the ſtone-gravel or any viſcous coagulated mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which may cauſe a ſuppreſſion of urine, or ſtrangury. By the balſamic vertue. Heals ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriations of the urinary paſſages, cauſed by attrition of the ſtone and gravel, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimony of Urine, and mitigates the pain. Very ſubtile and reſolutive, powerful to diſſolve the ſtone; diuretical &amp; purging by urine.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is half a Dram, which is about the quantity of a haſel nut.</p>
               <p>Take it thus five or ſix mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſting: roll it in fine powdered Sugar or Hony and ſo ſwallow it; then drink a good draught of White-wine after, or mixed with Ale. And you may follow your buſineſs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Nephritic Powder,</hi> clenſeth the Reins and bladder from ſand and gravel, opens the Uriters and Urinary paſſages, provokes Urine, cooles the reins and prevents the ſtone.</p>
               <p>Take it in a glaſſe of White-wine faſting, half a douzen mornings together. But let the Powder be put into the wine over night and ſtand cloſe covered.</p>
               <p>The Doſe is one Dram.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dyſuretic Powder,</hi> corrects the ſharpneſs of Urine (having an Hoſtile quality and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:30498:64"/>to acidityes) which cauſeth the Uriters to twitch and vellicate with a painful Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive motion and contraction in the ſmall of the back and hips to the Region of the bladder and bottom of the Belly: helps incontinency of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine or debility of holding water, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sphincter Muſcle of the bladder and taking away the acrimony of the Urine, which provokes the expulſive faculty: it checks the over ſtrong attraction of the reines, cauſing immoderate making water, thereby waſting the body, exhauſting the natural humidity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhing the Maſſe of bloud: coagulates a ſaline and tartareous reſolution in the body which comming into the ductures of the Vrine, ſtimulates and irritates to expulſion by its acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Cooles the reins, mitigates the ardor and ſcalding heat of Vrine.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is a Dram, for the age 14. two ſcruples: 8 years old half a Dram.</p>
               <p>Take it in the morning an hour before you riſe, in poſſet drink: you may eat or drink when you are up and go abroad. Vſe it a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night or three weeks together. Obſerve your diet; and let your drink be ſteeled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:30498:65"/>
               <head>For the Genital Parts.</head>
               <p>THE Reſtaurative eſſence, aſiſts digeſtion in the Spermatic veſſels, ſtrengthens the generative faculty; effectual againſt ſterility or barrenneſſe in the feminine ſex, and deficiency in the maſculine; if the cauſes be ſuperfluous moiſture, crudity and infaecundity of the ſeed, debility of the Genital parts, frigidity or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity of nature, and not organical impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and defects. It ſtrengthens a weak back, preſerves the balſom of nature, and natural heat; reſtores conſumptive weak perſons, ſtrengthens old age, and the declinings of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; refreſheth the animal and vital ſpirits by its aromatical fragrancy; roborates the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal parts; aſiſts the digeſtions, prevents crudityes and the ſuperfluity of crude hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</p>
               <p>Taketh away putrefaction in bodyes that have a ranke or ſtrong favour, by reaſon of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid humors breathing forth through the pores of the body; it will depurate, clenſe and make ſuch bodyes more ſweet and wholeſome, and more acceptable to their bed fellows.</p>
               <p>Shake the bottle, before you uſe it.</p>
               <p>Drop it into fine powdered ſugar and take it upon a knifes point: then drink a glaſſe of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:30498:65"/>Tent, Muskadel, or Sack, after it.</p>
               <p>The Doſe is 24 drops for Men or Women.</p>
               <p>You may take it night and morning in bed.</p>
               <p>In the uſe of ſtrengthning Medicines, Take this obſervation: That if the body be ſoul, let gentle purgation precede; firſt clenſe, then ſtrengthen, thats a regular courſe: for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, let women take the <hi>Hyſterical Pills;</hi> Men may uſe the <hi>Stomack</hi> or <hi>Cachectic Pills:</hi> As the condition of their body moſt requires.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hyſterical Pills,</hi> have an abſterſive, and purgative faculty, to clenſe and open obſtructions of the veins leading to the Matrix, whereby the terms may have their due times, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, according to the courſe of nature: they diſſipate flatulent vapours, and evacuate nox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious humors collected in the womb, which having aquired maligne qualities by reſidence there, occaſions various ſymptomes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance in ſeveral parts by conſent from the Matrix: as <hi>Hypochondriac</hi> Melancholy, palpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the heart, ſhortneſs of breath and compreſſion about the ſtomack, pains of the head, <hi>deliriums,</hi> Convulſive motions, ſadneſs, paleneſſe and unwonted Complection; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent fits of the Mother, diſperſe the vapours, and corrects the malignant cauſe: They cure the Green Sickneſſe, brings the termes into their right order, reſtores the Complexion,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:30498:66"/>and purgeth the lower Region of the body.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is 6 pills; for fifteen years old, 5 pills; or but four, if ſhe be a tender body and eaſie to operate.</p>
               <p>Take them early in the Morning, you may lye an houre after: when you are up drink a good draught of warm Poſſet, and walk in the Houſe. Eat at noon.</p>
               <p>Thus do two or three days together: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit ſo many days, then take twice or thrice more. And you will finde the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Expulſive Powder,</hi> Is appointed for a difficult and perilous Child birth; being ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to expedite the delivery of Women in a ſlow hard labour: it procures travelling pains when nature is unable and weak, giveth ſtrength to the woman and Child, and haſtens the Birth; expells a dead child, and brings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the after burden.</p>
               <p>You may give it twice in twelve hours, for the foreſaid occaſions, not oftner.</p>
               <p>The Doſe is one paper of powder.</p>
               <p>Take it in a ſmall ſpoonful of Cinnamon-Water Penyroyal-Water, or Mace Ale; or theſe mixed at the diſcretion of the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:30498:66"/>
               <p>The <hi>Reſtringent Powder,</hi> helps the debility and weakneſs of the Spermatic Veſſels, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by immoderate coition, or other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: ſtayes a Gonorhaea or Running of the Reins, ſo called; corrects the heat and acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſeed that ſtimulates to expulſion, and allays the pain: aſſwageth any ſharp hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in the privities of either Sex, heals an exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or excoriation there; takes away itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or moleſting heat; prevents the danger by immoderate copulation, cools, allayes and ſtrengthens thoſe parts,</p>
               <p>Uſe it thus: Take a quart of Smiths water, let it ſtand ſix hours to ſettle, then pour off a pinte cleer, in it put the Powder, ſhake it well in a Bottle; then with a Syringe inject it into the privy part morning and night, and you will receive much help and eaſe.</p>
               <p>But if the Gonorrhaea be virulent, proceeding from the Pox; then it is requiſite alſo that you take the Medicines proper for that diſeaſe, as the italic and neapolitan Pills, to purifie and clenſe your body from that malignity and virulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy where with the humors are tainted and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated; And to prevent future danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:30498:67"/>
               <head>For the joynts.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Arthritick Pills,</hi> are peculiarly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the Gout, whether heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or acquired by diaetetic errors, or differing in the part affected; as the feet, knees hips, hands or other Joynts; yet owning the ſame approxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate cauſe, and admit the ſame cure. They attract the ſerous acrid humor which pricks and lancinates the <hi>Perioſtium</hi> and nervous parts about the Joynt: and retract the conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of humors (cauſed by pain) reſorting to the part affected. They are very profitable and Auxiliary againſt a rheumatiſmus (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the running Gout) which is an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratic pricking pain wandring from part to part, cauſed by a flatulent acrimonious humor, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting not only the joynts but the <hi>perioſtia</hi> of the Bones between joynt and joynt, the Muſcles of the body, and membranes of the internal viſcera: they prevent fluxion and tranſition of turgid humors, evacuates biting Choler, Saline and ſharp Serous humors. And checks the ſero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of their nature. By their alkaliſate quality, they deſtroy exotic acidities which are dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and hoſtile to neru us and and membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous parts, and are a ſingular prophylactic or preſervative from the cruelty of arth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritick
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:30498:67"/>arthritic or Gout pains. Uſe them Spring and Autume for prevention: or at other ſeaſons if occaſion require.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is 5 Pills: for feminine and tender bodyes eaſy to operate, 4 may be ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Take them early in bed, lye an hour or two after; drink a little poſſet when they work, and eat at noon: Do ſo two or three days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; intermit 4 or 5 dayes, and take again.</p>
               <p>After Purgation the <hi>Sudorifio Pills</hi> are bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicines">
               <head>For the Skin.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Coſmetick Water,</hi> is appointed for diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourations and commaculations of the skin; native or adventitious, (accounted no ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity with the Ladyes) being ſymptomes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting the conſtitution, &amp; temperature of ſome principal parts, diſeaſes preſent and imminent, or the <hi>veſtigia</hi> and markes of preceding infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and external accidents, diſplayed in their proper diſtinguiſhing colours, citrine, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, brown, red, ſwarthy &amp;c. According to the nature of their cauſes, as in both the jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:30498:68"/>Scurvy, diſtempered Livers and Spleens, obſtructions, and moſt Cachectic bodyes, ſmall-Pox, Meaſels, Contuſions, burns &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This waſhing is no fucus that ſayes an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial colour upon the skin to palliate a bad complexion and deceive the ſight. But to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and tiear a dark brown skin, of the face, neck, breaſt or bands: it takes away Sun-burn, roughneſs, ſwarthineſs, Morphew, ſmall Pox ſpots and pimplex hath an abſterſive and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating faculty to thin and puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a muddy thick skin which clouds the luſtre of a lively peircing aſpect.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more amiable then the life, which is preſented to view with ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition, being vailed with the skin, which if dark and thick, eclipſes and hides much of the luſtre and penetration.</p>
               <p>But if thin, clear and more tranſparent, the glory and beauty of the life then ſtreams forth with great attraction: And therefore the eye is the moſt lovely victorious part, for its dilucid clearneſs, in which the ſparklings and vigour of life is moſt viſible and naked. 'Tis not white and red that hath the magnetiſme of love, but the life dreſſed in thoſe perſpicuous colours.</p>
               <p>You may uſe or leave this water when you will without prejudice, there is no Mercury not any thing to injure the tendereſt skin.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:30498:68"/>
               <p>Shake the Bottle, then wet a cloath with it and waſh your face every morning.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Powder of Saturn</hi> is appointed for <hi>Cuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defaedations,</hi> venereous Scab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Vlcers, puſtules knobs in the fleſh and glandulous tumors From the venereous cauſe. Alſo Scabs and Vlcers from other cauſes; Tettars, Ringworms itch, puſhes, pimples. Chilblanes, cooles all outward inflammations, repreſſeth tumors and aſſwageth their pain, very profitable for Sores or Tumors of the Kings evil.</p>
               <p>Vſe it thus: take a quart of Smiths water let it ſtand to ſettle; then pour of a pinte and halfe clear, in it put the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and let it boil gently to a pinte, in a glaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bottle ſet in a Kettle of water; then let it ſtand 2 dayes to ſettle very clear; poure it off and keep it for uſe: and with this liquor bathe the places affected morning and night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <head>For the Venereal Pox.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Italic Pills,</hi> are a ſpecific purgative Medicine for the Venereal <hi>Pox.</hi> They purge and clenſe the body by their appropriate vertue from the virulency and foulneſs of that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:30498:69"/>diſeaſe, which corrupts the whole maſſe of bloud, and breaks forth into puſtul's, Scabs and Vicers, by time invading the ſolid parts; they mitigate pain, checkes and abates the rigour of other ſymptomes which attends this diſeaſe, and prevents the danger.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is 5 Pills.</p>
               <p>Take them early in bed, lye an hour after; and when they work, drink a little poſſet-drink: you may eat at noon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Neapolitan Pills,</hi> are a Peculiar Sudori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic Medicine for the great <hi>Pox</hi> after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding purgation, to tranſpire and breath out by ſweating the remaining malignity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious infection wherewith the body is taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They diſpell the maligne vapours, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive the ſpirits oppreſſed, purifie the bloud, and eradicate the impurity and venenate quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the diſeaſe, by their peculiar propriety and oppoſition.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is 4 Pills.</p>
               <p>Take them in bed eaily, or at night if more convenient for your occaſions; half an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter drink a draught of hot bear or poſſet drinke wherein Sage is boiled be covered warm and lye to ſweat when you have ſweat 2 hours, (not longer) let ſome cloaths be taken of and cool by degrees, and have a care you take not cold after ſweating, the Pores being open.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:30498:69"/>
               <head>A regular and eaſie cure for the Venereal Pox with the preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Medicines.</head>
               <p>THis diſeaſe ſometimes lyes obſcure and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be dettcted, and puts on the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of other infirmities, but thoſe who are guilty of the danger, may conclude by ſome of the following ſymptoms, what it is that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and alters them. Yet this foul diſeaſe is not alwaies got by impure copulation; But otherwiſe ſometimes, Man with Man, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with Woman, lying together, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intimate Society. And although it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, yet all bodies are not apt to receive it, as all catch not the Plague in an infected houſe. But I muſt ſhorten the diſcourſe, and come to the ſymptomes which attend the diſeaſe, and they are various according to the degree and heigth arrived at. At firſt a laſſitude, weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indiſpoſition to motion, heavineſs and dulneſs, the Spirits being tainted and opreſſed with the infection: pain of the head, ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and other parts, cheifly at night: heat and burning in the palmes of the hands and ſoles of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:30498:70"/>the feet: a Gonorrhae a or running of the Reins: afterwards breakings out upon the skin vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous buboes, and Ulcers of the privy parts, &amp;c. Which come not altogether, but ſucceſſively by degrees, diſcovering the diſcaſe in its progreſs, and degree of malignity.</p>
               <p>The cure is performed thus; the firſt day take a Doſe of the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alic pills; the ſecond day let a vein be opened, if you be Feavoriſh or of a hot conſtitution; take blood at the diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Chyrurgeon. The fourth day take the Italic pills again; reſt the fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh: the eight day take the Italic pills again: the tenth, eleventh, twelfth dayes take the Neapolitan Pills to ſweat; then reſt 2 or 3 dayes, and take the Italic pills again; and after that, the Neopolitan. As occaſion requires continuance.</p>
               <p>This method you are to obſerve for a ſhort or longer time, according to the greatneſs and inveterate contumacy of the diſeaſe. Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chainging theſe Medicines and giving conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reſpite: which courſe will not be hard for you to obſerve although your body be weak and brought low with the diſeaſe, for nature will ſtrengthen and be much incouraged dayly, by the aſſiſtance of theſe Medicines and Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal courſe, prevailing upon the diſeaſe. And you will be more cheerful and ſtrong then at firſt when you began.</p>
               <p>In the interim during this courſe and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:30498:70"/>no day is prohibited but you may uſe the powder of Saturne, if there be any Ulcer, puſtuls, Scabs, or tumors cauſed by this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe: alſo the Reſtringent powder if there be a Gonorrhaea: and if your mouth be fore, or the gums ſwelled and tender by reaſon of the malignant humor ſpending it ſelf that way by ſpitting, as ſometimes it doth; then uſe to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle your mouth often with hot broth, or warm Beer ſweetned with hony, and you need not fear any prejudice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <head>Haematic Powder.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Haematic Powder</hi> is appointed as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary help to reſt ain an immoderate Flux of blood that is hurtful and weakning to nature; whether it be the overflowing of womens monthly purgations, vomiting or ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of blood, Haepatic Fluxes by Stool, by Vrine, or at the noſe. It corrects the acrimony, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity or ſeroſity, and heat of blood which ſtimulates to expulſion, and cauſeth tranſuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, apertion, or eroſion of a vein It incraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſates and thickens the blood; And makes it indiſpoſed for fluxion, conſtringeth and bindes the Veſſels and aſſiſts the dibility of the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:30498:71"/>
               <p>Take it in a draught of Verjuice Poſſet cold, morning and night in bed.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is one Dram: for twelve years old, half a dram.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <head>Febrific Elixir.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Febrific Elixir,</hi> is very auxiliary to mitigate and allay the burning heat of Fevers; it checks the fermenting ebulliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and aeſtuation of the blood; reſiſts febrific pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction and diſpoſeth to tranſpiration of hot putrid vapours, which cauſeth reſtleſneſs and unquiet watchings; aſſwageth immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thirſt, irrigates and refreſheth the parched ſpirits: excites decayed appetite by reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtomachical ferment, and is grateful to the ſtomack.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is twenty drops: for young peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo many drops as they are years old.</p>
               <p>Shake the bottle when you uſe it.</p>
               <p>You may take it in a glaſs of White-wine: or mingled with freſh ſmalbeer equal parts, a good draught; twice in the day, or night. You may put Syrup of Oranges or Lemmons if you will to it, for the Pallate ſake; you need not fear the heat of the wine to prejudice you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:30498:71"/>
               <head>Sarcotic <hi>Pills.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Sarcotic Pills</hi> are appointed for Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers internal and external, they exſiccate clenſe and heal by their <hi>Balſamick</hi> vertue, excoriations and ulcers within the body, where there is a poſſibility of cure; taking away all corroſive and ſharp fretting humors, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues the ulceration: they are very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious towards the cure of external ulcers and ſores in any part of the body, ſubtracting the antecedent cauſe, evacuating ſerous acrid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which feeds the ſore and prohibites heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: they are proper and beneficial for wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, to expedite their cures: they are good for Scabbed perſons, Leprous, or have any breakings out upon the skin.</p>
               <p>The Doſe for Man or Woman is 5 or 6 Pills: for 14 years old. 4 Pills.</p>
               <p>Take them 3 or 4 mornings in a week; you may lie an hour or 2 after them in bed. 3 hours after taking them, you may drinke poſſet drink, or whey: Which alſo is beſt for your common drink, in the forementioned caſes, and to have it ſteeled with gads of ſteel quenched there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:30498:72"/>
               <head>Sudorific Pills</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Sudorific Pills</hi> are aperitive, reſolutive and diſcuſſive; opens the pores and procures breathing ſweats; removes Cold, Aches, and ſtiffneſs in the Muſcles and joints; tranſpires and breaths out putrid vapours and ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of crudy watery humors and rheumatic moiſture; depurates and clenſeth the bloud; and opens obructions: very profitable in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſions or bruiſes, diſſipates and ſcatters the Flux of humors reſorting to the dolorous part affected, and prevents coagulation of the bloud, reſolves it if already fixed and congealed; they prevent tumors, and internal apoſtumation, and diſperſeth a colleciton of humors. A general Medicine, and may fitly be uſed in all caſes that require ſweating, with facility and benefit.</p>
               <p>You may take them 2 or 3 mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſting, in bed covered warm; a quarter of an hour after, drink a draught of hot poſſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drink, then ſweat will break forth, lye in it for 2 hours; then take off clothes by degrees, and cool with diſcretion.</p>
               <p>The full Doſe is 4 Pills: for 14 years old, 3 Pills.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:30498:72"/>
               <head>Sympathetic Powder.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Sympathetic Powder,</hi> is of known ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in cureing green wounds, as alſo the Tooth-ach.</p>
               <p>Take a few drops of bloud from the wound, in a peice of linnen, &amp; lay upon the bloud a little of this powder; then tye it up cloſe, and put it in your boſome, and keep it warm day and night, for if cold or wet happen to it, the wounded perſon will be much diſturbed and pained. If there be wounds in ſeveral parts, each wound muſt have a ſeveral cloth uſed in like manner, waſh the wound with white-wine, or the parties urine; then binde up the wound with convenient linnen cloth that cold come not to it, and in ſuch manner as the brims of the wound may draw towards each other: the third day open the wound and waſh away the quittour or corruption, then bind it up again with freſh clothes, and you will have a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cure, if the wound be in ſuch a part of the body as is cureable. In like manner you may do to a beaſt wounded, with ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>For the Tooth-ach thus: cauſe your gum to bleed where the pain is, with a pen-knife or needle; then ſtain a cloth with it the breadth of a groat, without rheum; then lay a little pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it; tie it up and keep it as aforeſaid, and it ſeldom fails to give preſent eaſe and cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="medicine">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:30498:73"/>
               <head>Iſſue Cere-cloth</head>
               <p>THE Iſſue Cerecloth is very commodious for thoſe who have Iſſues in any part of the body, it attracts and draws to the place for vent, extravafated, ſuperfluous, erratic humors: cauſeth a dry Iſſue to run, and brings away fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy matter; prevents inflammation and keeps an Iſſue coole: very neceſſary in journyes and voyages; one peice will ſerve a month in wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then lay on a freſh one; wipe it and turn the other ſide to the place every dreſſing, and lay a paper upon it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:30498:73"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the Diſeaſes and Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes for which the Medicines are peculiarly appointed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>PAlſy,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lethargy,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Convulſions,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Falling-Sickneſs,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vertigoe</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Head-ach,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tremors,</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rheums,</hi> page 80. 81. 114.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bad hearing</hi> page 80. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bad ſight</hi> page 80, 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coughs,</hi> page 82. 83.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſumption,</hi> page 82. 83. 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spitting blood,</hi> page 82. 83.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Short breath,</hi> page 82, 83.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ill ſavoured breath,</hi> page 82, 83, 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Palpitation of the heart,</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fainting.</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oppreſſion at heart and ſtomack,</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Melancholy vapours,</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bad Stomack,</hi> page 87, 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Surfets,</hi> page 85, 87.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pain at ſtomack,</hi> page 87. 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wind,</hi> page 85,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worms,</hi> page 87, 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cholick,</hi> page 87.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coſtiveneſs,</hi> page 96.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fluxes,</hi> page 87, 95.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jaundice,</hi> page 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gripings,</hi> page 87.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spleen,</hi> page 90, 91, 92.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scurvy,</hi> page 90, 91, 92.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſtructed Liver</hi> page 90.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dropſies,</hi> page 93, 94.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obſtructed Meſentery,</hi> page 90,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stone and gravel</hi> page 98, 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Infirmities of the Urine,</hi> page 98. 99.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> page 103.</item>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:30498:74"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Green-Sickneſs.</hi> page 101.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Them immoderate,</hi> page 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fits of the Mother</hi> page 101.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barrenneſs,</hi> page 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maſculine Imbecillity,</hi> page 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hard-labour,</hi> page 102.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Weak backs,</hi> page 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fevers,</hi> page 85. 112.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plague,</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Small-Pox,</hi> page 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meaſels</hi> page 58.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French-Pox,</hi> page 170. 180. 109.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poyſons,</hi> page 58.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gout.</hi> page 104.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nkneſs of body,</hi> page 100.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inflamations,</hi> page 107.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tumors,</hi> page 107.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers,</hi> page 107. 113.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bruiſes,</hi> page 114.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aches,</hi> page 114.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stiffneſs,</hi> page 114</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scabs,</hi> page 107, 103.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Itch,</hi> page 107. 103.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tettes,</hi> page 108.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ring-worms,</hi> page 107.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swarthyneſs</hi> page 150. 160.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sun-burn,</hi> page 150. 160.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Morphew,</hi> page 150. 160.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spots,</hi> page 105. 160.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chilblains,</hi> page 107.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Initia Morborum quamvis levia ſerpunt, Venienti occurrite—</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:74"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:75"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:75"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:76"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:30498:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:30498:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:30498:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:30498:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:30498:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:30498:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:30498:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:30498:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:30498:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_medicine_prices">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:30498:83"/>
            <head>The Medicines are appointed at theſe Rates; that none may give more; or expect them for leſs.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">s.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">d</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CApital Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cephalic Eſſence</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Pectoral Electuary</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Balſamic Extract</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cordial Tincture</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bezoardic Confection</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Stomack Pills.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Digeſtive Elixir</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cachectic Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Scorbute Tincture</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hydropic Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hydropic Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aperitive Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Retentive Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nephritic Extract</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nephritic Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dyſuretic Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Reſtaurative Eſſence</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hyſterical Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:30498:84"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Expulſive Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Reſtringent powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Arthritic Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Coſmetic Water</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Powder of Saturn</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Italick Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Neapolitan Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Haematic Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Febrific Elixir</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sarcotic Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sudorific Pills</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sympathetic Powder</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iſſue Cerecloth</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>WHat Medicines you intend to keep for emergent occaſions, ſet them in dry places from moiſture and they will remain in full vertue, the Electuaries a year and half; the Pills and powders two years: the Elixirs, Tinctures, Extracts and Eſſences many years, being cloſe ſtopt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30498:84"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
